<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Webdev | Bits, Bytes, and Words]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.zimmerman.io/categories/webdev/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.zimmerman.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-10T13:46:54-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.zimmerman.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Zimmerman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jake@zimmerman.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intro to Columns in HTML]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/12/26/intro-to-columns-in-html/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-26T12:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/12/26/intro-to-columns-in-html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>HTML and CSS can be frustrating when first starting out. Despite all you try, nothing is in the right place. I&rsquo;ve advised more than a few friends on how to figure out this mystery and I&rsquo;ve noticed a pattern: people don&rsquo;t realize they should be using a grid.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Positioning Content</h2>

<p>When something doesn&rsquo;t align correctly on the page, a natural phrase to Google is &ldquo;make div align right&rdquo; or &ldquo;move div up.&rdquo; In other media where content is positioned absolutely, like when using text boxes in Microsoft Word, these might be the right queries. With HTML &amp; CSS, though, they&rsquo;re off point. Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, there&rsquo;s definitely a time for <code>position: absolute</code>, but if this comes up when you&rsquo;re trying to make grids you&rsquo;re likely on the wrong path.</p>

<p>In HTML, the page is drawn from top to bottom, left to right. This means that your page ends up being aligned how words in a book are. Once the first word has taken up a certain amount of space, the next word starts filling up the space after it. The trick then, is knowing <em>how much</em> space the first item takes up, and how to resize it appropriately so that the second item &ldquo;falls into place.&rdquo;</p>

<h2>Blocks and Inline Elements</h2>

<p>The easiest way to explain block and inline elements is to continue our book analogy. Block elements are like titles and headings&mdash;they take up the entire page width, spanning from the left border to the right border. That&rsquo;s why if you put two headings as close as possible to each other, they&rsquo;ll still each have their own lines. There&rsquo;s no &ldquo;room&rdquo; for it to be any other way! Meanwhile, inline elements are like individual words. Where one word stops, the next one begins. A word takes up no more space than is required to size it compactly.</p>

<p>Disregarding some special cases, <em>every HTML element</em> falls into one of these two categories. Below are some examples of block elements and inline elements:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center;"> Block </th>
<th style="text-align:center;"> Inline   </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> <code>div</code> </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> <code>span</code>   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> <code>h1</code>  </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> <code>a</code>      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> <code>p</code>   </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> <code>strong</code> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> <code>ul</code>  </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> <code>em</code>  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> <code>li</code>  </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> <code>br</code>     </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> <code>pre</code> </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> <code>button</code> </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>We know that we need to use a div to house our columns. The problem is, divs are a block elements, so they&rsquo;ll span the whole width of the page. Luckily, there&rsquo;s a relatively simple (though non-intuitive) fix to get our divs to line up.</p>

<h2>Floating Content</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take a look at what we&rsquo;ve got so far. We want to have two columns, so our HTML is going to look like this:</p>

<p>&#8220;`html HTML for two columns</p>

<div class="row">
  <div class="left column">
    <!-- Your left content here -->
  </div>
  <div class="right column">
    <!-- Your right content here -->
  </div>
</div>


<pre><code>
Straightforward enough. Knowing what we know about block elements, what if we just set the width of the columns to 50%?
</code></pre>

<p>.column {
  /<em> arbitrary value for this example </em>/
  height: 300px;</p>

<p>  width: 50%;
}</p>

<p>/<em> so we can tell them appart </em>/
.left { background: red; }
.right { background: blue; }
&#8220;`</p>

<p><a href="http://codepen.io/Z1MM32M4N/pen/qENvdx?editors=110">Let&rsquo;s try it out and see what happens</a></p>

<p>Uh oh, it looks like our columns aren&rsquo;t next to each other! In fact, it looks suspciously like something we mentioned earlier: if two page headings are as close together as possible, they&rsquo;ll still be placed on their own lines. We can verify that this is the case by using the <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/devtools">Chrome dev tools</a>. Inspecting the red div, we see the culprit:</p>

<p><a class="image-link" href="/images/left-column-margin.png"><img src="/images/left-column-margin.png"></a></p>

<p>For those familiar with the Chrome dev tools, that yellow-orange box is Chrome&rsquo;s attempt to show us the invisible <em>margin</em> present on our div. Since divs are block elements, by default there&rsquo;s enough margin on the div to make it fill up the whole width of the page.</p>

<p>The solution, if you saw from the CodePen, is to add the property <code>float: left</code> to the columns. This essentially instructs the browser not to add that extra margin: instead of being positioned absolutely between the two sides of the screen, it should float to one side and forget about the other. This leaves room for the second column to file into place next to it.</p>

<p>Go <a href="http://codepen.io/Z1MM32M4N/pen/qENvdx?editors=110">back to the pen</a> and uncomment the relevant line. <a href="http://codepen.io/Z1MM32M4N/pen/XJKGdg?editors=110">Observe</a> that we&rsquo;ve accomplished exactly what we wanted to.</p>

<h2>Going Forward</h2>

<p>Cool, this solves the problem of having two columns! What&rsquo;s next?</p>

<ul>
<li>How would we make three columns? Four columns? Twelve columns?</li>
<li>Once we have multiple columns, how can we skip columns? (<strong>Hint</strong>: just because we have a column doesn&rsquo;t mean we have to put something in it)</li>
<li>We can add multiple rows by duplicating the outer &ldquo;row&rdquo; div.

<ul>
<li>What if we want two 33%-width columns in the first row, but one 33%-width column in the second row? (This is actually a good one to work through. You might want to look into the <code>clear: both</code> CSS property)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The <code>border-left</code> and <code>border-right</code> CSS properties allow us to add a border to a div. We can even use <em>fancy CSS queries</em> (see below) to only add a border in between columns. But if we add a border, the columns overflow onto their own rows! Can you fix this?

<ul>
<li><strong>Warning</strong>: this one is the hardest. You will want to look into <code>box-sizing: border-box</code> and the &ldquo;CSS box model&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Services like <a href="http://codepen.io/">CodePen</a> and <a href="http://jsfiddle.net/">JSFiddle</a> are excellent tools for trying out little experiments like this. I encourage you to actually tinker around with the <a href="http://codepen.io/Z1MM32M4N/pen/XJKGdg?editors=110">starter code from before</a> to see how you can answer all of these small questions.</p>

<p>As it turns out, HTML/CSS grids are a very heavily studied point of design. So much so, that people build entire <em>CSS frameworks</em> around providing the building blocks to make grids easily. Here&rsquo;s a list:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://getbootstrap.com/">Bootstrap</a></li>
<li><a href="http://foundation.zurb.com/">Foundation</a></li>
<li><a href="http://semantic-ui.com/">Semantic UI</a></li>
<li><a href="http://unsemantic.com/">Unsemantic</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Bootstrap is by far the most common (once you see it, you&rsquo;ll start to realize how many sites look incredibly similar). However, many people misuse Bootstrap their first time around. <a href="http://www.helloerik.com/the-subtle-magic-behind-why-the-bootstrap-3-grid-works">This article</a> demystifies and documents how and why the Bootstrap 3 grid works.</p>

<p>Even once you&rsquo;re an HTML and CSS master, it can still be frustrating. (Actually, I&rsquo;d believe it if the experts were the most frustrated!). I love answering question and trying to explain things, so if you need some help working through the exercises above or you&rsquo;re working on a personal project, I&rsquo;d love to see if I can help out! Protip: put your code on GitHub or somewhere else that&rsquo;s easily accessible so that it&rsquo;s easy to share changes quickly.</p>

<h2>Appendix</h2>

<p>I mentioned an example about &ldquo;fancy CSS queries&rdquo; above. This is certainly advanced territory, but it&rsquo;s something that I get asked a lot by beginners so here goes.</p>

<p>Basically, the problem is that you only want vertical line separators in between columns, not on the edges. In ASCII art:</p>

<pre><code class="plain Beautiful ASCII Art Diagram">
        |        |
  col1  |  col2  | col 3
        |        |

        ^        ^
        | these. |
</code></pre>

<p>(Thank you, thank you, I know my drawings are beautiful XD).</p>

<p>You already know that you can use <code>.class</code> and <code>#id</code> to select items based on their classes and IDs. But there are <a href="http://code.tutsplus.com/tutorials/the-30-css-selectors-you-must-memorize--net-16048">tons more query selectors</a> you can use! I&rsquo;ll use one to accomplish what we want with the vertical dividers:</p>

<pre><code class="css Super Fancy CSS Selectors">.column {
  height: 300px;
  /* Try uncommenting me! */
  float: left;
  width: 50%;
  /* this kind of solves the "overflow" exersise I posted above YOLO */
  box-sizing: border-box;
}

/* marvel at the fanciness! */
.column:not(:last-child) {
  border-right: 5px solid black;
}

.left { background: red; }
.right { background: blue; }
</code></pre>

<p>You can combine this with a nice padding (<code>padding: 50px</code> should do the trick) on the <code>.column</code>, and you&rsquo;ve got yourself a vertical divider!</p>

<h2>Update</h2>

<p>After writing this post, I discovered a couple articles talking about the new
<code>flexbox</code> feature. From what I can tell, it looks promising in terms of ease of
use and browser compatibility. That being said, many common CSS frameworks still
use <code>float: left</code>, so the content presented here is still good information to
know. If you&rsquo;re having trouble getting floats to work, though, maybe you should
look into <code>flexbox</code> instead!</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on
[GitHub][g] or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. If this post was about one of
my open source projects, make sure to star it on GitHub! I love hearing what
people think, so feel free to comment, open an issue, or send me an email.
 [g]: https://www.github.com/jez/
 [h]: https://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Google OAuth2 for CMU Authentication]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/10/20/using-google-apps-for-cmu-authentication/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-20T05:11:37-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/10/20/using-google-apps-for-cmu-authentication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Using <code>python-social-auth</code> and Django, I&rsquo;ve found a very straightfoward way of adding authentication to apps designed for CMU students. Given that all Andrew accounts are now Google Apps @ CMU accounts, we can take advantage of the widely used Google OAuth2 libraries to authenticate users, but just restrict sign-ins to the <code>andrew.cmu.edu</code> &ldquo;hosted domain.&rdquo;</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Background</h2>

<p>Finally! I&rsquo;ve alluded many times to blogging about some of the things I&rsquo;m learning from my experiences rewriting <a href="http://print.scottylabs.org/">Print@ScottyLabs</a>. After a summer of putting it off and half a semester more of dawdling, I&rsquo;ve finally managed to lay some solid groundwork.</p>

<p>One of the features that we plan on adding to Print 2.0 is a web interface. For people familiar with the way Print works currently, you interact with the service entirely through email. This leads to a clunky user experience and a lot of weird bugs and edge cases. With a web interface, we hope to streamline the process of account management and printing documents.</p>

<p>With this in mind, we needed to decide on a user model. Ideally, we&rsquo;d like this model to give us two things:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>It should be secure.</strong> People who don&rsquo;t already have access to CMU printers shoudn&rsquo;t be able to easy gain access by using our system.</li>
<li><strong>It should be familiar.</strong> We want to design Print 2.0 to be as close to an official-feeling CMU app as we can without stepping on the ever-present administrative toes.</li>
</ul>


<p>Naturally, this leads to an obvious solution: have people sign in using the same <a href="https://login.cmu.edu">https://login.cmu.edu</a> site, which is used for email, Blackboard, AutoLab, and many other on-campus services. The trick, then, is to figure out how to do this.</p>

<p>My first thought was to &ldquo;use Shibboleth.&rdquo; I put this in quotes because I didn&rsquo;t exactly know what that meant at the time. What I was looking for was a simple OAuth2 API (like what Google or Facebook provide) that I could much just drop into my app with no other configuration required on the deployment machine. Shibboleth does not offer this solution.</p>

<p>Luckily, Google&rsquo;s OAuth2 API has a feature that allowed me to do exactly what I wanted. Thanks to a couple of resourceful members of the CMU Computer Science Facebook group (Carlos Diaz-Padron and Arthur Lee), I found out about a barely-documented parameter that you can pass in on the auth URL to restrict Google OAuth2 logins to a <a href="https://developers.google.com/accounts/docs/OAuth2Login#hd-param">specific hosted domain</a>. Since all CMU Andrew accounts are Google Apps accounts (as of Fall 2013), we can ask Google to restrict logins to the <code>'andrew.cmu.edu'</code> hosted domain. From here on, the only trick is to get whatever client library you&rsquo;re using to handle authentication to pass this parameter with a value of <code>'andrew.cmu.edu'</code> along to Google. The rest of this post describes a bare-bones way of doing this using Django.</p>

<h2>Implementing Authentication</h2>

<p>The following is a pretty long-winded explanation of my personal struggles with this. If you&rsquo;d really just like to learn by example and by making your own mistakes, check out the <a href="https://github.com/jez/google-apps-cmu-login/">code on GitHub</a>. I also found the <a href="https://github.com/omab/python-social-auth/tree/master/examples/"><code>python-social-auth</code> examples</a> very helpful. In the spirit of <a href="http://www.gitorial.com/">gitorial</a>, the commits are structured logically to give you a sense of how the app came together as I wrote it. In fact, I&rsquo;ve even <a href="http://www.gitorial.com/#/jez/25536683">made a gitorial</a> for this repo!</p>

<h3>Python Social Auth</h3>

<p>First up: pick a client library. I&rsquo;ve had success using <code>python-social-auth</code> in other projects, and it&rsquo;s generally a mature project, so it&rsquo;s what I picked.</p>

<p>Next up: skim the docs. Given the enormous size of this project (it has solutions for tons of python frameworks and tons of authentication backends), the docs are pretty comprehensive. Unfortunately, they fell short in the one place where I needed to look.</p>

<p>One of the neat things about the python social auth library is that it can be easily extended to support additional authentications backends using simple object-oriented techniques. To make this happen, very few pieces of information are hardcoded; in particular, the names of the variables that allow for configuration are dynamically generated based on the available backends.</p>

<p><a href="https://python-social-auth.readthedocs.org/en/latest/configuration/settings.html#extra-arguments-on0auth-processes">This page</a> outlines how to pass in extra, optional arguments while constructing the redirect URI for a particular authentication backend. It hints at the names of the variables that need to be defined, but sadly these hints are wrong.</p>

<p><strong>This is a correction to the documentation provided at the above link.</strong> Extra authentication arguments can be passed in using any of the following variables:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>SOCIAL_AUTH_&lt;backend&gt;_AUTH_EXTRA_ARGUMENTS</code></li>
<li><code>SOCIAL_AUTH_AUTH_EXTRA_ARGUMENTS</code> (no, this is not a typo)</li>
<li><code>AUTH_EXTRA_ARGUMENTS</code></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m not sure what the difference between using the second and third variables are, but all variables of the first form will allow you to scope the extra arguments to a particular backend (in case you&rsquo;re using more than one in the same app).</p>

<p>So in my case, I added the following line to my <code>settings.py</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="python settings.py https://github.com/jez/google-apps-cmu-login/blob/master/config/settings.py#L66">SOCIAL_AUTH_GOOGLE_OAUTH2_AUTH_EXTRA_ARGUMENTS = {'hd' : 'andrew.cmu.edu'}
</code></pre>

<p>Phew. That&rsquo;s a long variable name. But Jake, how did you come up with <code>GOOGLE_OAUTH2</code> for the backend name? There&rsquo;s really no good answer to this, because I haven&rsquo;t been able to find a web-readable list of all the names in one place. The way this name is generated is by taking the <code>name</code> property of the particular backend you&rsquo;re using (in my case, <code>social.backends.google.GoogleOAuth2</code> has <code>name = 'google-oauth2'</code>, which I found by looking at the source), replacing all hyphens with underscores and making everything capital.</p>

<h3>The Django App</h3>

<p>Now you should plenty of background knowledge to make sense of the Django app on your own, but I&rsquo;ll reiterate the main points here for completeness. It will be pretty choppy in most places if you&rsquo;re not referring to my example app on GitHub as you read.</p>

<p>First, we&rsquo;ll get all our URLs in place. For Django, all the URLs dealing with logging in are already defined; we just have to include them:</p>

<pre><code class="python config/urls.py https://github.com/jez/google-apps-cmu-login/blob/master/config/urls.py#L10">    ...
    url(r'', include('social.apps.django_app.urls', namespace='social')),
    ...
</code></pre>

<p>Then we can set up some simple URLs (a home page and a logout view), and accompanying views for these URLs that do exactly what you think they should.</p>

<p>In our template, if the user is logged in, we&rsquo;ll show their AndrewID (<code>user.username</code>), or else we&rsquo;ll hardcode the link to the Google OAuth2 authentication backend.</p>

<p><strong>Note</strong>: if you plan on using multiple forms of authentication (like Facebook or GitHub) in this app, be sure to check out the python social auth example for how they generate their home page such that no URLs need to be hard coded. For our purposes, though, if there&rsquo;s only one URL it will be fine to just write it out.</p>

<h3>Demo</h3>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/GYRUvTvTSJE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h3>Going Forward</h3>

<p>That&rsquo;s basically it. The rest is up to you to fill in. Building off this model, you should be able to make basically any Django app that you&rsquo;d otherwise want to build.</p>

<p>One thing you&rsquo;ll want to look into is defining a custom Auth User model. Custom Auth User models allow you to plug into Django&rsquo;s default auth system to take advantage of all the features it has available for keeping track of your users. The <a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/topics/auth/customizing/">Django docs</a> on this topic are actually pretty good, though you&rsquo;ll likely want to find an example to help you work through the specifics.</p>

<p>As always, let me know if you have any questions or if by following these steps something didn&rsquo;t work for you. Because of how bare bones this app is, it&rsquo;s likely that I glossed over some points for the sake of minimalism. Comment below with your feedback and feel free to email me or make GitHub issues with your questions.</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on
[GitHub][g] or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. If this post was about one of
my open source projects, make sure to star it on GitHub! I love hearing what
people think, so feel free to comment, open an issue, or send me an email.
 [g]: https://www.github.com/jez/
 [h]: https://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Everyone Loves JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/15/why-everyone-loves-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-15T23:39:52-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/15/why-everyone-loves-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Airbnb has put together a stellar list of simple ways to make your JavaScript more maintainable and manageable. From comments and whitespace, to hoisting and type casting, this list covers nearly everything you should know when developing a JavaScript app.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Backstory</h2>

<p>Before I begin, I should mention that any views I express here are entirely my own. Now, I recently began working for the summer at Bloomberg L.P., where for the first few days we sit through a few talks and do a few labs that introduce us to the technologies we&rsquo;ll be using throughout the summer. JavaScript was one of these languages, and I found that a quote on the first slide is all too correct:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;JavaScript is both the most popular and unpopular programming language.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ndash; Doug Crockford</p></blockquote>

<p>From there, as you might imagine, the reactions from a predominantly C++ oriented audience towards JavaScript&rsquo;s quirks were pretty amusing. There are some significant differences between these two languages, and if you&rsquo;re not careful, they can get annoying quite quickly.</p>

<h2>Links</h2>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/airbnb/javascript">airbnb/javascript</a></h3>

<p>JavaScript might have it&rsquo;s quirks, but it&rsquo;s still a vastly powerful language, especially if used well. For any aspiring JavaScript developer, I would highly recommend looking over Airbnb&rsquo;s JavaScript best practices. Even if you think you&rsquo;ve got the language down, I&rsquo;m confident you&rsquo;ll uncover something useful.</p>

<h3><a href="https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/the-birth-and-death-of-javascript">The Birth and Death of JavaScript</a></h3>

<p>While you&rsquo;re here, check out this video for an incredibly humorous and satisfyingly accurate discussion of JavaScript, from birth to death.</p>

<h3><a href="https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/wat">Wat</a></h3>

<p>Aaand while we&rsquo;re posting humorous JavaScript videos, I&rsquo;ve gotta throw this one into the mix.</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on
[GitHub][g] or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. If this post was about one of
my open source projects, make sure to star it on GitHub! I love hearing what
people think, so feel free to comment, open an issue, or send me an email.
 [g]: https://www.github.com/jez/
 [h]: https://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HPSTR: An Octopress Theme]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/04/hpstr-an-octopress-theme/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-04T20:51:41-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/04/hpstr-an-octopress-theme</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In case you didn&rsquo;t notice, we&rsquo;re rocking a new theme: <a href="https://github.com/jez/hpstr-theme">HPSTR for Octopress</a>! Ported from the <a href="https://github.com/mmistakes/hpstr-jekyll-theme">theme of the same name</a> for Jekyll, this theme has a bunch of cool new features that make the theme easier to use and more customizable.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Before I begin, I have to give a huge shout out to <a href="https://github.com/mmistakes/">mmistakes</a> for crafting such an impeccable set of stylesheets and Jekyll templates. I could talk this theme up all day, but I think that the results speak for themselves. Even more praiseworthy is that the entire source code is licensed under the GPL, enabling anyone to take the source and build upon it. And on that note, I&rsquo;d like to unveil what <em>I&rsquo;ve</em> built.</p>

<h1>Ported to Octopress</h1>

<p>The theme was originally implemented for a vanilla Jekyll blog. Personally, I find the automation tools provided by Octopress to be incredibly helpful, and I didn&rsquo;t want to give these up to be able to deploy this theme. As a result, I had to tweak a few things in order to get it to work with a standard Octopress installation.</p>

<h2>Less to Sass</h2>

<p>The HPSTR theme was originally built using Less to compile its stylesheets. Octopress uses Sass under Compass instead&ndash;a decision which I love: the rich library of plugins that Compass provides is ridiculous. Thus, this was the first step of the port.</p>

<p>After a quick Google search I stumbled upon <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/14970224/anyone-know-of-a-good-way-to-convert-from-less-to-sass">this question</a> on Stack Overflow, which surprisingly took care of the vast majority of the conversion, leveraging mere text replacement. From there, it was mostly a matter of slugging through the Less docs to find out what a particular function did, jumping over to the Compass/Sass docs to find a corresponding mixin, and repeating.</p>

<h2>Sass to Compass</h2>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t stop after I had the vanilla Sass working. One of Compass&rsquo;s coolest features is that you don&rsquo;t have to repeat yourself: there are mixins for seemingly everything, and when there aren&rsquo;t, there are 3<sup>rd</sup> party plugins. Thus, the next phase of the port was to see how much of the code I could reduce to compass mixins.</p>

<p>For the most part, this stage affected CSS3 properties which need vendor prefixes, to include keyframe animations. The keyframe animations are particularly worthy of a mention because I found a handy plugin called <a href="https://github.com/ericam/compass-animation">compass-animation</a> to take care of them. It works as easily as any other Compass mixin, from installation to use.</p>

<h2>Octopress Mannerisms</h2>

<p>There are a few things that Octopress users can expect to be reasonably similar from one deployment to the next, and I wanted to ensure that as many of the features dually implemented by mmistakes and Octopress used the syntax or conformed to the style set forth by Octopress. A small example of this: the <code>page.link</code> and <code>page.external_url</code> properties. Defined by the old and new themes respectively, both accomplish a similar purpose. Each specifies that the main purpose of the post is to link to a different page. Not wanting to break the service for current Octopress users, I tried to convert as many of these subtleties.</p>

<p>On top of this, I restructured a lot of the original code so that someone used to customizing an Octopress theme would feel more at home when checking out the source for this theme, even if some of the particulars were different. This applied mostly to the Sass directory structure, but also to the templates.</p>

<h1>More Powerful Customization</h1>

<p>One of the many ways Octopress adds value on top of Jekyll is the ease with which you can get a Jekyll blog up and running, and subsequently customize and tweak that theme. This was one area where I felt that the original Jekyll theme fell short. The original stylesheets had a somewhat decent set of variables (in <code>less/variables.less</code>) that would allow you to customize the colors and font faces, but the method for customizing the size of the font was wonky (larger values produced smaller fonts), and the various mixins employed to handle setting the sizes were confusing.</p>

<p>To solve this, I added <em>loads</em> of new variables handling the font sizes and line heights on a per-component basis, while also providing a master switch to easily resize everything. My theme also differs here from the original in that it&rsquo;s default font size is slightly larger for normal paragraph text (the whole reason why I cared about customizing the font size in the first place!).</p>

<h1>Like what you see?</h1>

<p>This theme is in no way perfect, from the styles to the compatibility with the vast array of Octopress options. If my support for your favorite feature is lacking or absent altogether, patch it up and submit a pull request on <a href="https://github.com/jez/hpstr-theme">GitHub</a>!</p>

<p><strong>I&rsquo;d also love to hear about your installation process.</strong> If something didn&rsquo;t quite work out right when installing the theme from GitHub or everything went super smoothly, tell me on GitHub in an issue, on <a href="https://www.twitter.com/Z1MM32M4N">Twitter</a>, in the comments below, or in an <a href="mailto:jake@zimmerman.io">email</a>. Seriously!</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on
[GitHub][g] or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. If this post was about one of
my open source projects, make sure to star it on GitHub! I love hearing what
people think, so feel free to comment, open an issue, or send me an email.
 [g]: https://www.github.com/jez/
 [h]: https://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GitHub Pages Custom Domains]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/05/06/github-pages-custom-domains/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T02:15:35-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/05/06/github-pages-custom-domains</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I stumbled at first getting the DNS configured for my blog, because I&rsquo;ve got a slighty more complicated setup than normal. I decided to supplement the documentation <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> gives by recounting my personal example and the setup that worked.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>If you&rsquo;ve never heard of <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> for web hosting, you should definitely check it out. You basically get free hosting for any static (i.e. plain HTML or <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a>-served) website with git-push-to-deploy. You can even configure your site to be listed at a custom domain according to <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/setting-up-a-custom-domain-with-github-pages">these</a> instructions, which are pretty thorough. I feel like it&rsquo;d help, though, to supplement this documentation with a fairly common example setup.</p>

<h2>My setup</h2>

<p>I have two sites which I want to host using the <code>zimmerman.io</code> domain name: my <a href="//blog.zimmerman.io">blog</a> and my <a href="//www.zimmerman.io">personal site</a>. I host my personal site at <a href="//www.zimmerman.io">www.zimmerman.io</a>, but you can also navigate to <a href="//zimmerman.io">zimmerman.io</a> and end up in the same places as before. It&rsquo;s served as a User Page from <a href="https://www.github.com/jez/jez.github.io">this repo</a>.</p>

<p>I host my blog at <a href="//blog.zimmerman.io">blog.zimmerman.io</a>, and it&rsquo;s served as a Project Page in <a href="https://www.github.com/jez/blog/">this repo</a>.</p>

<h2>What the instructions say</h2>

<p>The instructions say a few things very clearly (yay, documentation!).</p>

<p>First, if I want to use a custom subdomain (like what I&rsquo;m doing for my blog) to host a repo, I can add a <code>CNAME</code> record with my DNS provider that points to what is in my case <code>z1mm32m4n.github.io</code>. This was counterintuitive to me, because I thought at first that this would make my blog.zimmerman.io domain redirect to my personal site, but that&rsquo;s not how GitHub handles it. (They&rsquo;re smarter than that.)</p>

<p>At the same time, I need to put a file in the root of the blog&rsquo;s repo (in the <code>gh-pages</code> branch because it&rsquo;s a Project Page), called <code>CNAME</code> (<a href="https://github.com/jez/blog/blob/gh-pages/CNAME">view source</a>) with the contents &lsquo;blog.zimmerman.io&rsquo;. After a little while, the DNS tables will update and everything here should work: I can now view my <em>blog</em> where I want it.</p>

<h2>What the instructions say, but not so clearly</h2>

<p>The next bit gave me some trouble at first (probably just because I was being impatient while the DNS tables were updating). The end goal was to have the <code>www</code> subdomain host my site and have the <code>@</code> (top-level or apex) domain redirect there. If you read carefully, the instructions say to do three things:</p>

<ol>
<li>Make the <code>CNAME</code> file (<a href="https://github.com/jez/jez.github.io/blob/master/CNAME">view source</a>) in my (User) Pages repository contain <code>www.zimmerman.io</code>. <strong>This</strong> is the domain at which I do want my site to be visible.</li>
<li>Create a <code>CNAME</code> record with my DNS provider pointing to <code>z1mm32m4n.github.io</code> for the <code>www</code> subdomain. From a technical standpoint on the DNS provider&rsquo;s side of things, this is the same thing we did before with the <code>blog</code> subdomain.</li>
<li>Create an <code>A</code> record pointing the <code>@</code> domain towards GitHub using the IP address they specify.</li>
</ol>


<p>This last step is where you have to have a little faith: nowhere is there an explicit file telling GitHub, &ldquo;If you get a request from zimmerman.io, send it to me!&rdquo; GitHub merely notices that there <strong>is</strong> a repo with a CNAME containing &lsquo;<strong>www</strong>.zimmerman.io&rsquo;, and so they say, &ldquo;Well, we may as well send this <strong>top level</strong> domain to the <strong>www</strong> domain referenced over here&hellip; I&rsquo;ve got nothing better to do.&rdquo;</p>

<p>This was a little confusing at first, because if I wanted the opposite direction (www.zimmerman.io to redirect to zimmerman.io), I would have still created a CNAME file, but it would have contained <code>zimmerman.io</code> and I would have created an <code>A</code> record with my DNS provider, not an actual CNAME. (I still did have to create both the <code>A</code> and <code>CNAME</code> in the end, but in this setup, the <code>A</code> record is referenced in the <code>CNAME</code> file, if that makes any sense.)</p>

<h2>Recap</h2>

<h3>My CNAME Files</h3>

<ul>
<li> For www.zimmerman.io:

<ul>
<li> CNAME file contains <code>www.zimmerman.io</code></li>
<li> CNAME file resides in <code>master</code> branch of User Pages repo for jez</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> For blog.zimmerman.io

<ul>
<li> CNAME file contains <code>blog.zimmerman.io</code></li>
<li> CNAME file resides in <code>gh-pages</code> branch of Project Pages repo for jez/blog</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h3>My DNS Config</h3>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a screenshot of what my records look like with my DNS provider, in case this was still unclear.</p>

<p><a class="image-link" href="/images/DNS-config.jpg"><img src="/images/DNS-config.jpg"></a></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m personally using <a href="https://www.gandi.net/">Gandi</a> for domain registration because they had the cheapest <code>.io</code> TLD registration, but their interface takes some getting used to. (It was certainly still worth the deal I got.)</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on
[GitHub][g] or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. If this post was about one of
my open source projects, make sure to star it on GitHub! I love hearing what
people think, so feel free to comment, open an issue, or send me an email.
 [g]: https://www.github.com/jez/
 [h]: https://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
