<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Best-practices | Bits, Bytes, and Words]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/categories/best-practices/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-13T20:21:43-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.zimmerman.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Zimmerman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jake@zimmerman.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Joys of the Craft]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/12/13/the-joys-of-the-craft/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-13T19:52:09-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/12/13/the-joys-of-the-craft</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while ago, I was given the book <em>The Mythical Man-Month</em>, by Frederick P. Brooks, Jr. I finally have some time to sit down and read it, and I&rsquo;m loving it. In the first chapter, this quote on &ldquo;the joys of the craft&rdquo; (i.e., programming) struck me as particularly on point:</p>

<!-- more -->


<blockquote><h3>The Joys of the Craft</h3>

<p>Why is programming fun? What delights may its practitioner expect as his reward?</p>

<p>First is the sheer joy of making things. As the child delights in his mud pie, so the adult enjoys building things, especially things of his own design. I think this delight must be an image of God&rsquo;s delight in making things, a delight shown in the distinctness and newness of each leaf and each snowflake.</p>

<p>Second is the pleasure of making things that are useful to other people. Deep within, we want others to use our work and to find it helpful. In this respect the programming system is not essentially different from the child&rsquo;s first clay pencil holder &ldquo;for Daddy&rsquo;s office.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Third is the fascination of fashioning complex puzzle-like objects of interlocking moving parts and watching them work in subtle cycles, playing out the consequences of principles built in from the beginning. The programmed computer has all the fascination of the pinball machine or the jukebox mechanism, carried to the ultimate.</p>

<p>Fourth is the joy of always learning, which springs from the nonrepearing nature of the task. In one way or another the problem is ever new, and its solver learns something: sometimes practical, sometimes theoretical, and sometimes both.</p>

<p>Finally, there is the delight of working in such a tractable medium. The programmer, like the poet, works only slightly removed from pure thought-stuff. He builds his castles in the air, from air, creating by exertion of the imagination. Few media of creation are so flexible, so easy to polish and rework, so readily capable of realizing grand conceptual structures. (As we shall see later, this very tractability has its own problems.)</p>

<p>Yet the program construct, unlike the poet&rsquo;s words, is real in the sense that it moves and works, producing visible outputs separate from the construct itself. It prints results, draws pictures, produces sounds, moves arms. The magic of myth and legend has come true in our time. One types the correct incantation on a keyboard, and a display screen comes to life, showing things that never were nor could be.</p>

<p>Programming then is fun because it gratifies creative longings built deep within us and delights sensibilities we have in common with all men.</p>

<p>&ndash; &ldquo;The Tar Pit&rdquo;, <em>The Mythical Man-Month</em>, Frederick P. Brooks Jr.</p></blockquote>

<p>Brooks of course follows this up with &ldquo;The Woes of the Craft&rdquo;, which is equally on point. I&rsquo;m only a few pages in, but I already feel like, respectfully, I&rsquo;ve learned more than I did in all of Tech Comm ([15-221][techcomm]). I would absolutely recommend it to anyone considering pursing software engineering!</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on [Twitter][t], checking out my tinkerings on [GitHub][g], or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. I&#8217;d love to hear what you think about what I&#8217;ve managed to put together, so feel free to comment, tweet at me, or send me an email.
 [t]: http://www.twitter.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [g]: http://www.github.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [h]: http://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running a VPS: Log 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/24/running-a-vps-log-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-24T22:11:14-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/24/running-a-vps-log-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Seriously: Back It Up</h1>

<p>I don&rsquo;t have the best track record with configuring servers. I&rsquo;ve certainly brought down a ScottyLabs server or two before, but sometimes there&rsquo;s no avoiding that in the sake of learning. At times like these, you&rsquo;ve just gotta reboot and try again. With DigitalOcean&rsquo;s auto-backups though, this process is incredibly easy.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>EncFS Troubles</h2>

<p>As part of my eventual goal of hosting my own mail, I tried following <a href="//sealedabstract.com/code/nsa-proof-your-e-mail-in-2-hours/">this post</a> to set up a mail server on my VPS. Unfortunately, I never even made it out the gates. The first step is to install and set up EncFS for letting you mount encrypted filesystems, which the tutorial was planning on using to store email securely. Unfortunately, after following the steps listed to a T, my poor VPS whined and complained about being misconfigured.</p>

<p><strong>Edit</strong>: After doing a little more research, I found that the root of my issue wasn&rsquo;t something I had been doing. Apparently, you have to <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-update-a-digitalocean-server-s-kernel-using-the-control-panel">manually update the kernel</a> through the DigitalOcean web console. You can read more about it on this <a href="https://github.com/al3x/sovereign/issues/147#issuecomment-43849647">GitHub issue</a>.</p>

<p>Regardless, my first attempt to do something cool on this new VPS was a dud. All I had to show for it was a muddled, no-longer-pristine VPS with some packages and libraries that simply didn&rsquo;t work. If I were to continue with the tutorial by skipping this step, I would have never known whether the cause of any future issue was something misconfigured at this step.</p>

<h2>The Day is Saved</h2>

<p>But then I remembered: DigitalOcean is automatically backing up my droplet! After logging into the web interface, all I had to do was click a button and my whole system was reset to the way it looked 24 hours prior. It was <em>actually that easy</em>.</p>

<p>Thus, for anyone getting started with a new server, whether it be on DigitalOcean or any other service (even a box you have running in your room), I cannot stress enough the value of automatic&ndash;or at least regular&ndash;backups. Not only is this a good idea to preserve data in the event of an outage, but it lends a seemingly unbounded ability to mess around and tinker.</p>

<p>What this means is that you get all the fun of learning cool, new Linux-y things, but without ever having to worry about whether you&rsquo;ll break the whole system. Sure, this mindset isn&rsquo;t necessarily the best to adopt for a production machine, but for my circumstances, all I want is free reign to experiment and break things to my heart&rsquo;s content.</p>

<h2>Back to Square One</h2>

<p>With my first attempt at installing a mail server foiled, I think for my next attempt I&rsquo;ll try a different path. Instead of installing and configuring everything more or less manually (I really wanted to do this for the experience of it all, learning the nitty-gritty of how it works), this time around I think I&rsquo;m going to give <a href="https://github.com/al3x/sovereign">sovereign</a> a try. I&rsquo;ve heard good things, and it is in fact based on the original tutorial I had found, so it&rsquo;s looking pretty promising as of yet.</p>

<p>Whatever happens though, I&rsquo;m feeling pretty good about the fact that I can turn things around with a single click.</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on [Twitter][t], checking out my tinkerings on [GitHub][g], or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. I&#8217;d love to hear what you think about what I&#8217;ve managed to put together, so feel free to comment, tweet at me, or send me an email.
 [t]: http://www.twitter.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [g]: http://www.github.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [h]: http://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running a VPS: Log 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/19/running-a-vps-log-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-19T22:10:51-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/19/running-a-vps-log-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Managing Dotfiles Across Machines</h1>

<p>You could say I&rsquo;m a bit of a geek when it comes to configuring my terminal environment; this obsession has led me to concoct ever-elaborate setup scripts and configuration files. On top of this, between my laptop&rsquo;s multiple boot environments, the servers I use for school, work, and ScottyLabs, and now <a href="/2014/06/19/running-a-vps-log-0">metagross</a>, keeping my configuration files in sync is a must. I handle it swiftly using a combination of git and rcm.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>My Scripts</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve put a decent amount of time into my dotfiles. I like to think they&rsquo;re pretty good. That being said, I&rsquo;m not about to go over every piece of them, because that would bore even me. I might come back to these pieces in a series on getting started with the terminal (aimed at incoming CS freshmen and other up-and-coming hackers), but for now, a link will suffice.</p>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles/">Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles</a></h4>

<h2>rcm + git</h2>

<p>rcm, short for rc file (as in .bash<b>rc</b>, .vim<b>rc</b>) management, is a tool that manages symlinks between dotfiles in one directory and your home directory. This is cool because, once all your config files contained in one folder, they can be tracked with git for version control without having to put your entire <code>$HOME</code> directory inside a git repo.</p>

<p>On a single machine, rcm works like this. You have one directory (usually <code>~/.dotfiles</code>, but configurable to any directory) which stores all the config files. In here, all files which are meant to be tracked and symlinked do <em>not</em> include the prefixed &lsquo;<code>.</code>&rsquo;; instead, it is added as part of the linking process. After installation, which is easily handled through the brew formula, the .deb, or the Makefile, there are a couple of new tools available.</p>

<p>The first worth mentioning is <code>man 7 rcm</code>, which documents what was just installed. Taking a glance at this page, we see that rcm is actually a suite of tools: <code>lsrc</code>, <code>mkrc</code>, <code>rcdn</code>, and <code>rcup</code>. While all these tools are useful, the most important is <code>rcup</code>. After collecting all your dotfiles into <code>~/.dotfiles</code>, simply executing <code>rcup</code> symlinks all the necessary files to their appropriate locations.</p>

<p>From here, you get all the benefits of git, like pushing to GitHub, collaborating with others, lightweight branching, and syncing files easily even when your workflow is distributed across many servers.</p>

<h2>Caveats</h2>

<p>To be fair, I don&rsquo;t use <code>rcm</code> in the way I think it&rsquo;s creators imagined it would be used. Specifically, the software includes certain provisions to designate which files should affect various machines using a tag system. While it could possibly work, in my mind it&rsquo;s much more tedious than what I&rsquo;ve come up with.</p>

<p>Succinctly, the issue is this: when cloning a repo and running <code>rcup</code> for the first time, you can&rsquo;t easily say &ldquo;this is my VPS, it&rsquo;s running Debian GNU/Linux, has these system binaries installed, and therefore should start up using these methods and scripts&rdquo;. For this, we&rsquo;re on our own.</p>

<h2>Installation</h2>

<p>The solution I came up with regarding a multiple-environment workflow deals with handling all the necessary machine-dependent configuration within my dotfiles <em>themselves</em>. That way I can minimize code reuse and have everything in one convenient file. As a result, <a href="https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles/tree/master/bash_profile">my bash_profile</a> is a bit lengthy at about 300 lines, and it has three large case statements, but I make all this up through deployment. Deployment is <strong>incredibly</strong> swift. Again, You can take a look at the file to see how it works, but when I had finished <a href="/2014/06/19/running-a-vps-log-1">locking down my server</a>, these are the only configuration commands I had to run:</p>

<p><figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Installing rcm and dotfiles </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;install rcm using deb and dpkg&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;<span class="nv">$ </span>wget &lt;a <span class="nv">href</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;https://thoughtbot.github.io/rcm/debs/rcm_1.2.3-1_all.deb&quot;</span>&gt;https://thoughtbot.github.io/rcm/debs/rcm_1.2.3-1_all.deb&lt;/a&gt;
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>sudo dpkg -i rcm_1.2.3-1_all.deb&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;clone dotfiles down, into the ~/.dotfiles directory&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;<span class="nv">$ </span>git clone &lt;a <span class="nv">href</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles&quot;</span>&gt;https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles&lt;/a&gt; ~/.dotfiles&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;make the symlinks&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;<span class="nv">$ </span>rcup
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

<p>Voilà! After that, I had my sick bash prompt, my <a href="/2014/06/11/update-your-software-its-the-law/">snazzy update function</a>, my delightful vim colorscheme, solarized dir colors&ndash;the list goes on and on.</p>

<p>Sure, it&rsquo;s taken a bit of effort to get the point where I can run these commands and have it Just Work, but doing that work once means that from now on, whenever I sit down at a new work computer, a new VPS, a new laptop, or some other workstation, I&rsquo;m only a few commands away from my favorite settings.</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on [Twitter][t], checking out my tinkerings on [GitHub][g], or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. I&#8217;d love to hear what you think about what I&#8217;ve managed to put together, so feel free to comment, tweet at me, or send me an email.
 [t]: http://www.twitter.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [g]: http://www.github.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [h]: http://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Everyone Loves JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/15/why-everyone-loves-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-15T23:39:52-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/15/why-everyone-loves-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Airbnb has put together a stellar list of simple ways to make your JavaScript more maintainable and manageable. From comments and whitespace, to hoisting and type casting, this list covers nearly everything you should know when developing a JavaScript app.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Backstory</h2>

<p>Before I begin, I should mention that any views I express here are entirely my own. Now, I recently began working for the summer at Bloomberg L.P., where for the first few days we sit through a few talks and do a few labs that introduce us to the technologies we&rsquo;ll be using throughout the summer. JavaScript was one of these languages, and I found that a quote on the first slide is all too correct:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;JavaScript is both the most popular and unpopular programming language.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ndash; Doug Crockford</p></blockquote>

<p>From there, as you might imagine, the reactions from a predominantly C++ oriented audience towards JavaScript&rsquo;s quirks were pretty amusing. There are some significant differences between these two languages, and if you&rsquo;re not careful, they can get annoying quite quickly.</p>

<h2>Links</h2>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/airbnb/javascript">airbnb/javascript</a></h3>

<p>JavaScript might have it&rsquo;s quirks, but it&rsquo;s still a vastly powerful language, especially if used well. For any aspiring JavaScript developer, I would highly recommend looking over Airbnb&rsquo;s JavaScript best practices. Even if you think you&rsquo;ve got the language down, I&rsquo;m confident you&rsquo;ll uncover something useful.</p>

<h3><a href="https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/the-birth-and-death-of-javascript">The Birth and Death of JavaScript</a></h3>

<p>While you&rsquo;re here, check out this video for an incredibly humorous and satisfyingly accurate discussion of JavaScript, from birth to death.</p>

<h3><a href="https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/wat">Wat</a></h3>

<p>Aaand while we&rsquo;re posting humorous JavaScript videos, I&rsquo;ve gotta throw this one into the mix.</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on [Twitter][t], checking out my tinkerings on [GitHub][g], or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. I&#8217;d love to hear what you think about what I&#8217;ve managed to put together, so feel free to comment, tweet at me, or send me an email.
 [t]: http://www.twitter.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [g]: http://www.github.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [h]: http://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Update Your Software: It's the Law]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/11/update-your-software-its-the-law/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T21:22:57-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/11/update-your-software-its-the-law</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, so maybe the government won&rsquo;t come after you for not updating. But they should. To guard off any present or future threats (be they from governments, security vulnerabilities, or something else in the cyber realm), I wrote a short bash snippet to check my system for outdated packages.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Obligatory Existential/Meta Section</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t quite know what prompted me to suddenly become interested in maintaining an up to date system. Maybe it was <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/cmuscs/permalink/727878180603546/">this post</a> of Arch Linux horror stories. Maybe it was the release of <a href="https://git.kernel.org/cgit/git/git.git/tree/Documentation/RelNotes/2.0.0.txt">git 2.0</a>, which introduces a lot of cool new features and deprecates a lot of others. Who knows, maybe it was influenced by Heartbleed and the <a href="https://www.openssl.org/news/secadv_20140605.txt">host</a> <a href="http://grahamcluley.com/2014/06/feedly-blackmail-ddos/">of other</a> <a href="http://blog.evernote.com/blog/2013/03/02/security-notice-service-wide-password-reset/">high-profile</a> security vulnerabilities and hacks that have sprung up lately. It&rsquo;s probably a combination of all of these. Let&rsquo;s move on.</p>

<p>For the impatient among us, here&rsquo;s the code, which is also available <a href="https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles/blob/master/bash_profile#L16-L42">here</a> and <a href="https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles/blob/master/bash_profile#L153-L178">here</a> amongst all the code for <a href="https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles">all my dotfiles</a>.</p>

<p><figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Alert to Update <a href="https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles/blob/master/bash_profile#L16-L42">https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles/blob/master/bash_profile#L16-L42</a> </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
<span class='line-number'>32</span>
<span class='line-number'>33</span>
<span class='line-number'>34</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;<span class="p">&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>ndash<span class="p">;</span> daily updates <span class="p">&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>ndash<span class="p">;</span>&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;<span class="o">[</span> ! -e <span class="nv">$HOME</span>/.last_update <span class="o">]</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>amp<span class="p">;&amp;</span>amp<span class="p">;</span> touch <span class="nv">$HOME</span>/.last_update&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;Initialize <span class="k">for</span> when we have no GNU date available&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;last_check<span class="o">=</span>0
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">time_now</span><span class="o">=</span>0&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;Unix last <span class="nb">command </span>to check the log of logins, grab the most recent&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;last_check_string<span class="o">=</span>&lt;code&gt;ls -l <span class="nv">$HOME</span>/.last_update <span class="p">|</span> awk <span class="s1">&#39;{print $6&quot; &quot;$7&quot; &quot;$8}&#39;</span>&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;Darwin uses BSD, check <span class="k">for</span> gdate, <span class="k">else</span> use date&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;if <span class="o">[[</span> &lt;code&gt;uname&lt;/code&gt; <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span>Darwin<span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>amp<span class="p">;&amp;</span>amp<span class="p">;</span> -n &lt;code&gt;which gdate&lt;/code&gt; <span class="o">]]</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">then</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nv">last_login</span><span class="o">=</span>&lt;code&gt;gdate -d<span class="s2">&quot;$last_check_string&quot;</span> +%s&lt;/code&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nv">time_now</span><span class="o">=</span>&lt;code&gt;gdate +%s&lt;/code&gt;
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">else</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="c"># Ensure this is GNU grep</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">if</span> <span class="o">[</span> -n <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span>&lt;code&gt;date --version 2<span class="p">&amp;</span>gt<span class="p">;</span> /dev/null <span class="p">|</span> grep GNU&lt;/code&gt;<span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span> <span class="o">]</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">then</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">last_login</span><span class="o">=</span>&lt;code&gt;date -d<span class="s2">&quot;$last_login_string&quot;</span> +%s&lt;/code&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">time_now</span><span class="o">=</span>&lt;code&gt;date +%s&lt;/code&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">fi</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">fi</span>&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;time_since_check<span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$((</span>time_now <span class="o">-</span> last_login<span class="k">))</span>&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;if <span class="o">[</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span><span class="nv">$time_since_check</span><span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span> -ge <span class="m">86400</span> <span class="o">]</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">then</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span><span class="nv">$cred</span><span class="o">==</span>&gt;<span class="nv">$cwhiteb</span> Your system is out of date!<span class="nv">$cnone</span><span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>lsquo<span class="p">;</span>Run &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt; to bring it up to date.<span class="p">&amp;</span>rsquo<span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">fi</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

<p><figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Check for Updates <a href="https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles/blob/master/bash_profile#L153-L178">https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles/blob/master/bash_profile#L153-L178</a> </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
<span class='line-number'>32</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;<span class="p">&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>ndash<span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">function</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;&amp;</span>mdash<span class="p">;</span>-&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;update<span class="o">()</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  touch <span class="nv">$HOME</span>/.last_update&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;  <span class="c"># Mac updates</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">case</span> <span class="nv">$HOSTNAME</span> in
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;em&gt;Jacobs-MacBook-Air&lt;/em&gt;<span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span><span class="nv">$cblueb</span><span class="o">==</span>&gt;<span class="nv">$cwhiteb</span> Updating Homebrew<span class="p">&amp;</span>hellip<span class="p">;</span><span class="nv">$cnone</span><span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      brew update&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">&quot;$cblueb==&amp;gt;$cwhiteb Checking for outdated brew packages...$cnone&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  brew outdated --verbose
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">&quot;$cblueb==&amp;gt;$cwhiteb Checking for outdated rbenv...$cnone&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nb">cd</span> <span class="nv">$HOME</span>/.rbenv
</span><span class='line'>  git fetch
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">if</span> <span class="o">[</span> <span class="s2">&quot;`git describe --tags master`&quot;</span> !<span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">&quot;`git describe --tags origin/master`&quot;</span> <span class="o">]</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">then</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">&quot;rbenv (`git describe --tags master`) is outdated (`git describe --tags origin/master`).&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">&quot;To update, run: cd ~/.rbenv; git merge origin master &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd -&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">fi</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nb">cd</span> - 2<span class="p">&amp;</span>gt<span class="p">;&amp;</span>amp<span class="p">;</span><span class="m">1</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>gt<span class="p">;</span> /dev/null
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">&quot;$cblueb==&amp;gt;$cwhiteb Checking for outdated ruby gems...$cnone&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  gem outdated
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">;;</span>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;  <span class="k">esac</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

<p>You&rsquo;ll note the use of a touch file (created in line 2 of the first snippet if it doesn&rsquo;t already exist). If this file is 24 hours old, each time this code is run an alert will be printed. Since this code is running inside of my <code>.bash_profile</code>, that means that every time I open a terminal on a 24-hour-old system, I see the update message.</p>

<p>Next, you&rsquo;ll note that I&rsquo;ve defined a function called <code>update</code> which is actually misnamed. This function merely checks for available updates instead of actually performing the updates, logging those packages, gems, and formulae it finds that are out of date. For my purposes, I only need to update brew, check for formulae updates, update rbenv, and check for gem updates. Obviously though, given that there is a way to programmatically check something for updates, plugging that code in here would check it as well. This means that this method is very easy to customize and extend for various needs.</p>

<h2>Rant</h2>

<p>I was planning on checking pip for updates as well, but pip is kind of not even good. To give you an idea, to check all the packages brew manages for updates, you type <code>brew outdated</code>, and it will list the formula name, current version number, and newest version number. Meanwhile, back in the land of pip, no such functionality exists (at least, simple functionality, and functionality that I could find. If you&rsquo;d like to correct me, be my guest!). I&rsquo;m sure that this script will grow as I come to manage more and more pieces of software on my system and others.</p>

<p>If you have any questions about what I&rsquo;ve done here, or you catch some bugs, be sure to comment below or file an issue on GitHub! I&rsquo;d love to hear what you have to say.</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on [Twitter][t], checking out my tinkerings on [GitHub][g], or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. I&#8217;d love to hear what you think about what I&#8217;ve managed to put together, so feel free to comment, tweet at me, or send me an email.
 [t]: http://www.twitter.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [g]: http://www.github.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [h]: http://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
