<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: design | Bits, Bytes, and Words]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-09-02T17:34:49-04:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.jez.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Zimmerman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jake@zimmerman.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Solarized LaTeX Listings]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2014/10/04/solarized-latex-listings/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-04T06:35:05-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2014/10/04/solarized-latex-listings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Out of the box, LaTeX listings are pretty bad. With a bit of work, you can ascribe some colors to the code, but you&rsquo;re still stuck with choosing a theme. Given that I recently just switched to the Solarized colorscheme in Vim and iTerm2, I made a LaTeX package that styles code listings with the predefined Solarized light colors.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2><a href="https://github.com/jez/latex-solarized">Source</a></h2>

<p>The source for this theme is on GitHub, and the README has pretty good documentation. Here&rsquo;s an example of the final result:</p>

<p><a class="image-link" href="/images/solarized-light-screenshot.png"><img src="/images/solarized-light-screenshot.png"></a></p>

<p>After you install them in the right place, you can include <code>\usepackage{solarized-light}</code> to turn source code listings light (as in above), <code>\usepackage{solarized-dark}</code> to have listings styled with the dark Solarized theme, and just <code>\usepackage{solarized}</code> to have access to the raw Solarized color codes (see the source for their names).</p>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve done this, you just have to include your code in your LaTeX file using the <code>listings</code> packages. You might want to check out <a href="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/LaTeX/Source_Code_Listings">the LaTeX wiki</a> for more information on how to get started quickly with code listings, or <a href="http://mirror.hmc.edu/ctan/macros/latex/contrib/listings/listings.pdf">the official documentation</a> for a more comprehensive reference.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Molokai: An iTerm2 Color Scheme]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2014/06/07/molokai-an-iterm2-color-scheme/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-07T12:00:39-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2014/06/07/molokai-an-iterm2-color-scheme</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve used <a href="https://github.com/tomasr">tomasr</a>&rsquo;s vim color scheme <a href="https://github.com/tomasr/molokai">molokai</a> for a long time now. Recently I decided that the default iTerm2 colors were a little lack luster, so I ported over the main colors from this theme into an iTerm2 theme.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2><a href="https://github.com/mbadolato/iTerm2-Color-Schemes#molokai">Installation</a></h2>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t already have your iTerm2 colors configured or you&rsquo;re looking for a change, you should definitely check out <a href="https://github.com/mbadolato/iTerm2-Color-Schemes">iTerm2-Color-Schemes</a>, a GitHub repo by <a href="https://github.com/mbadolato">mbadolato</a> filled with tons of themes he&rsquo;s ported, collected, and been given.</p>

<p>You can see and install the <a href="https://github.com/mbadolato/iTerm2-Color-Schemes#molokai">Molokai theme</a> there.</p>

<h2>Screenshots</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t have too many good screenshots of this theme that aren&rsquo;t vim because I&rsquo;m actually using <a href="https://github.com/seebi/dircolors-solarized">solarized</a> dircolors for colorizing the output of my <code>ls</code> and related commands. However, there are still plenty of tools I use which resort to default ANSI colors to colorize their output, like <code>git</code> and <code>brew</code>. You can see a <code>git log</code> command along side a table of all ANSI color combinations resulting from this theme (this table can be a bit overwhelming: it&rsquo;s best to just look at the first two columns to get an idea of what the colors really look like).</p>

<p><a class="image-link" href="/images/molokai.png"><img src="/images/molokai.png"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
