<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: python | Bits, Bytes, and Words]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/categories/python/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-06-14T02:00:48-04:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.jez.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Zimmerman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jake@zimmerman.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Show where a Python package is used]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2015/06/12/show-where-a-python-package-is-used/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-12T02:36:05-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2015/06/12/show-where-a-python-package-is-used</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back I was doing some spring cleaning of my Python packages. I noticed
that there were a bunch of packages that I couldn&rsquo;t recall installing. I wanted
to know if I could safely remove them, so I wrote a simple bash script to tell
me called <code>pip-uses</code>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Source</h2>

<p>Rather than post the source here and let it get more out of date every time I
change it, you can find the source <a href="https://github.com/jez/bin/blob/master/pip-uses">on GitHub</a>. It&rsquo;s in my <a href="https://github.com/jez/bin">bin
repository</a>, where I keep my notable helper scripts; feel free to
poke around.</p>

<h2>Motivations</h2>

<p>I was primarily influenced by Homebrew&rsquo;s <code>brew uses</code> command. It does a nice job
of giving you exactly the information you want, and I think the way the command
is named makes sense.</p>

<pre><code class="plain Homebrew: brew uses">$ brew uses --installed pango
imagemagick
</code></pre>

<p><code>pip-uses</code> gives you basically the experience:</p>

<pre><code class="plain Pip: pip-uses">$ pip-uses stevedore
virtualenvwrapper
</code></pre>

<p>In this example, the Python package <code>virtualenvwrapper</code> uses <code>stevedore</code>, just
as <code>imagemagick</code> uses <code>pango</code>. Both commands can save you from accidentally
removing a crucial dependency and answer the burning question, &ldquo;How in the world
did this thing get installed?&rdquo;</p>

<h2>Wish List</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m not doing much Python development these days, but if I had some spare time
I&rsquo;d love for the script to also have these features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Recursive enumeration of dependencies

<ul>
<li>It&rsquo;d be nice if <code>pip-uses</code> kept recursively searching until it found no more
dependencies. This way, it&rsquo;d be easy to see if you could safely uninstall a
whole slew of packages that you&rsquo;re no longer using.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Operate on more than one package

<ul>
<li>I didn&rsquo;t need it at the time, so I didn&rsquo;t implement it, but it&rsquo;d be nice if
the command took a variable amount of arguments and ran the same logic on
all supplied packages.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Integrate with <code>pip</code>

<ul>
<li>Programs like <code>brew</code> and <code>pip</code> allow developers to add &ldquo;external commands&rdquo;
by adding commands to the <code>PATH</code> that look like <code>brew-xyz</code> or <code>git-xyz</code>. I
couldn&rsquo;t find if there was a special way to add external commands to <code>pip</code>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>If you find this script useful and end up implementing one of these feature or
more on top of <code>pip-uses</code>, be sure to send me a Pull Request!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby Virtualenvs]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/ruby-virtualenvs/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-22T12:52:40-06:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/ruby-virtualenvs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back I found a command that removes all Ruby gems installed on a system
when you&rsquo;re using rbenv. It worked great, so I decided to build on top of it.
After a bit of research, I found a much better solution to the root of my
problems: sandboxing Ruby gems.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Ugh, Ruby&hellip;</h2>

<p>If you&rsquo;re anything like me, you can never do anything right on the first try
using Ruby. At one point, I found myself needing a script to just nuke
everything and start over&hellip; That&rsquo;s when I found Ian Vaughan&rsquo;s <a href="https://gist.github.com/IanVaughan/2902499">script</a> that
magically removes all gems. I was delighted to see that it worked perfectly on
the first try, and went about the rest of my business.</p>

<h2>Modifications</h2>

<p>There were two ways though in which this script&rsquo;s functionality differed from
what I wanted it to do: it always removed <strong>all</strong> gems, and it left behind a
<code>.ruby_version</code> file after it was used, clobbering any file that might have been
there before.</p>

<p>In my updated script, you can specify a list of ruby versions as arguments, and
it will only gems from those versions instead of all of them.  Also, it saves
and restores the value of the old <code>.ruby_version</code> file once it&rsquo;s done.</p>

<p>The new script is available <a href="https://gist.github.com/jez/cc2ba08062c6183a489c">as a fork of the original Gist</a> and also as
a part of of <a href="https://github.com/jez/bin/blob/master/uninstall_gems">my personal bin folder</a>.</p>

<h2>The Underlying Problem: Virtualenv&rsquo;s in Ruby</h2>

<p>After a bit of reflection, I realized I should be trying to solve the underlying
problem: different projects had different dependencies, and gems from one
project were bleeding into gems from another. If you&rsquo;re a Python developer, you
don&rsquo;t have this issue: <a href="http://virtualenvwrapper.readthedocs.org/en/latest/">virtualenvwrapper</a>, <code>pip</code>, and <code>requirements.txt</code>
files make this a non-issue.</p>

<p>After looking into if there existed a similar Ruby solution, I came up with
<a href="http://honza.ca/2011/06/install-ruby-gems-into-virtualenv">this blog post</a> outlining how you can do the exact same thing using
virtualenvs but with Ruby gems! Once again, it needed a little bit of
modification so that everything works again as you&rsquo;d expect when you
<code>deactivate</code>. Add these lines to your virtualenv&rsquo;s <code>postactivate</code> script:</p>

<pre><code class="python $VIRTUAL_ENV/bin/postactivate">export OLD_GEMHOME="$GEM_HOME"
export GEM_HOME="$VIRTUAL_ENV/gems"

export OLD_GEM_PATH="$GEM_PATH"
export GEM_PATH=""

export OLD_PATH="$PATH"
export PATH="$GEM_HOME/bin:$PATH"
</code></pre>

<p>And then add this complementary section to your <code>predeactivate</code> script:</p>

<pre><code class="python $VIRTUAL_ENV/bin/predeactivate">export GEM_HOME="$OLD_GEM_HOME"
unset OLD_GEM_HOME

export GEM_PATH="$OLD_GEM_PATH"
unset OLD_GEM_PATH

export PATH="$OLD_PATH"
unset OLD_PATH
</code></pre>

<p>Now, whenever you install gems, they&rsquo;ll install to the folder
<code>$VIRTUAL_ENV/gems/</code> instead of the system&rsquo;s location, so no gems bleed into
another project!</p>

<h2>One Step Further</h2>

<p>Bringing up this web page, copying those snippets, and pasting them in the two
necessary files every time is a bit tedious. To automate this process, we can
tap into virtualenvwrapper&rsquo;s configurability using hooks. Instead of dropping
those snippets into <code>$VIRTUAL_ENV/bin/{post,prede}activate,</code>, place them in
<code>$VIRTUALENVWRAPPER_HOOK_DIR/{post,prede}activate</code>.</p>

<p>Now every time you <code>workon</code> a virtualenv, the appropriate configuration will
be set up. Note that this means every normal Python project you use will have
this Ruby configuration added (not just the Ruby projects), but that shouldn&rsquo;t
matter because they interoperate nicely. If it&rsquo;s really an issue, you can stick
with the per-virtualenv solution above.</p>

<p>Note: a side effect of this nice sandboxing is that you can normally run
commands without prefixing them with <code>bundle exec ...</code>, which is actually really
handy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Google OAuth2 for CMU Authentication]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2014/10/20/using-google-apps-for-cmu-authentication/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-20T06:11:37-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2014/10/20/using-google-apps-for-cmu-authentication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Using <code>python-social-auth</code> and Django, I&rsquo;ve found a very straightfoward way of adding authentication to apps designed for CMU students. Given that all Andrew accounts are now Google Apps @ CMU accounts, we can take advantage of the widely used Google OAuth2 libraries to authenticate users, but just restrict sign-ins to the <code>andrew.cmu.edu</code> &ldquo;hosted domain.&rdquo;</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Background</h2>

<p>Finally! I&rsquo;ve alluded many times to blogging about some of the things I&rsquo;m learning from my experiences rewriting <a href="http://print.scottylabs.org/">Print@ScottyLabs</a>. After a summer of putting it off and half a semester more of dawdling, I&rsquo;ve finally managed to lay some solid groundwork.</p>

<p>One of the features that we plan on adding to Print 2.0 is a web interface. For people familiar with the way Print works currently, you interact with the service entirely through email. This leads to a clunky user experience and a lot of weird bugs and edge cases. With a web interface, we hope to streamline the process of account management and printing documents.</p>

<p>With this in mind, we needed to decide on a user model. Ideally, we&rsquo;d like this model to give us two things:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>It should be secure.</strong> People who don&rsquo;t already have access to CMU printers shoudn&rsquo;t be able to easy gain access by using our system.</li>
<li><strong>It should be familiar.</strong> We want to design Print 2.0 to be as close to an official-feeling CMU app as we can without stepping on the ever-present administrative toes.</li>
</ul>


<p>Naturally, this leads to an obvious solution: have people sign in using the same <a href="https://login.cmu.edu">https://login.cmu.edu</a> site, which is used for email, Blackboard, AutoLab, and many other on-campus services. The trick, then, is to figure out how to do this.</p>

<p>My first thought was to &ldquo;use Shibboleth.&rdquo; I put this in quotes because I didn&rsquo;t exactly know what that meant at the time. What I was looking for was a simple OAuth2 API (like what Google or Facebook provide) that I could much just drop into my app with no other configuration required on the deployment machine. Shibboleth does not offer this solution.</p>

<p>Luckily, Google&rsquo;s OAuth2 API has a feature that allowed me to do exactly what I wanted. Thanks to a couple of resourceful members of the CMU Computer Science Facebook group (Carlos Diaz-Padron and Arthur Lee), I found out about a barely-documented parameter that you can pass in on the auth URL to restrict Google OAuth2 logins to a <a href="https://developers.google.com/accounts/docs/OAuth2Login#hd-param">specific hosted domain</a>. Since all CMU Andrew accounts are Google Apps accounts (as of Fall 2013), we can ask Google to restrict logins to the <code>'andrew.cmu.edu'</code> hosted domain. From here on, the only trick is to get whatever client library you&rsquo;re using to handle authentication to pass this parameter with a value of <code>'andrew.cmu.edu'</code> along to Google. The rest of this post describes a bare-bones way of doing this using Django.</p>

<h2>Implementing Authentication</h2>

<p>The following is a pretty long-winded explanation of my personal struggles with this. If you&rsquo;d really just like to learn by example and by making your own mistakes, check out the <a href="https://github.com/jez/google-apps-cmu-login/">code on GitHub</a>. I also found the <a href="https://github.com/omab/python-social-auth/tree/master/examples/"><code>python-social-auth</code> examples</a> very helpful. In the spirit of <a href="http://www.gitorial.com/">gitorial</a>, the commits are structured logically to give you a sense of how the app came together as I wrote it. In fact, I&rsquo;ve even <a href="http://www.gitorial.com/#/jez/25536683">made a gitorial</a> for this repo!</p>

<h3>Python Social Auth</h3>

<p>First up: pick a client library. I&rsquo;ve had success using <code>python-social-auth</code> in other projects, and it&rsquo;s generally a mature project, so it&rsquo;s what I picked.</p>

<p>Next up: skim the docs. Given the enormous size of this project (it has solutions for tons of python frameworks and tons of authentication backends), the docs are pretty comprehensive. Unfortunately, they fell short in the one place where I needed to look.</p>

<p>One of the neat things about the python social auth library is that it can be easily extended to support additional authentications backends using simple object-oriented techniques. To make this happen, very few pieces of information are hardcoded; in particular, the names of the variables that allow for configuration are dynamically generated based on the available backends.</p>

<p><a href="https://python-social-auth.readthedocs.org/en/latest/configuration/settings.html#extra-arguments-on0auth-processes">This page</a> outlines how to pass in extra, optional arguments while constructing the redirect URI for a particular authentication backend. It hints at the names of the variables that need to be defined, but sadly these hints are wrong.</p>

<p><strong>This is a correction to the documentation provided at the above link.</strong> Extra authentication arguments can be passed in using any of the following variables:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>SOCIAL_AUTH_&lt;backend&gt;_AUTH_EXTRA_ARGUMENTS</code></li>
<li><code>SOCIAL_AUTH_AUTH_EXTRA_ARGUMENTS</code> (no, this is not a typo)</li>
<li><code>AUTH_EXTRA_ARGUMENTS</code></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m not sure what the difference between using the second and third variables are, but all variables of the first form will allow you to scope the extra arguments to a particular backend (in case you&rsquo;re using more than one in the same app).</p>

<p>So in my case, I added the following line to my <code>settings.py</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="python settings.py https://github.com/jez/google-apps-cmu-login/blob/master/config/settings.py#L66">SOCIAL_AUTH_GOOGLE_OAUTH2_AUTH_EXTRA_ARGUMENTS = {'hd' : 'andrew.cmu.edu'}
</code></pre>

<p>Phew. That&rsquo;s a long variable name. But Jake, how did you come up with <code>GOOGLE_OAUTH2</code> for the backend name? There&rsquo;s really no good answer to this, because I haven&rsquo;t been able to find a web-readable list of all the names in one place. The way this name is generated is by taking the <code>name</code> property of the particular backend you&rsquo;re using (in my case, <code>social.backends.google.GoogleOAuth2</code> has <code>name = 'google-oauth2'</code>, which I found by looking at the source), replacing all hyphens with underscores and making everything capital.</p>

<h3>The Django App</h3>

<p>Now you should plenty of background knowledge to make sense of the Django app on your own, but I&rsquo;ll reiterate the main points here for completeness. It will be pretty choppy in most places if you&rsquo;re not referring to my example app on GitHub as you read.</p>

<p>First, we&rsquo;ll get all our URLs in place. For Django, all the URLs dealing with logging in are already defined; we just have to include them:</p>

<pre><code class="python config/urls.py https://github.com/jez/google-apps-cmu-login/blob/master/config/urls.py#L10">    ...
    url(r'', include('social.apps.django_app.urls', namespace='social')),
    ...
</code></pre>

<p>Then we can set up some simple URLs (a home page and a logout view), and accompanying views for these URLs that do exactly what you think they should.</p>

<p>In our template, if the user is logged in, we&rsquo;ll show their AndrewID (<code>user.username</code>), or else we&rsquo;ll hardcode the link to the Google OAuth2 authentication backend.</p>

<p><strong>Note</strong>: if you plan on using multiple forms of authentication (like Facebook or GitHub) in this app, be sure to check out the python social auth example for how they generate their home page such that no URLs need to be hard coded. For our purposes, though, if there&rsquo;s only one URL it will be fine to just write it out.</p>

<h3>Demo</h3>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/GYRUvTvTSJE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h3>Going Forward</h3>

<p>That&rsquo;s basically it. The rest is up to you to fill in. Building off this model, you should be able to make basically any Django app that you&rsquo;d otherwise want to build.</p>

<p>One thing you&rsquo;ll want to look into is defining a custom Auth User model. Custom Auth User models allow you to plug into Django&rsquo;s default auth system to take advantage of all the features it has available for keeping track of your users. The <a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/topics/auth/customizing/">Django docs</a> on this topic are actually pretty good, though you&rsquo;ll likely want to find an example to help you work through the specifics.</p>

<p>As always, let me know if you have any questions or if by following these steps something didn&rsquo;t work for you. Because of how bare bones this app is, it&rsquo;s likely that I glossed over some points for the sake of minimalism. Comment below with your feedback and feel free to email me or make GitHub issues with your questions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
