<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bash | Bits, Bytes, and Words]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/categories/bash/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-04-16T00:39:41-04:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.jez.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Zimmerman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jake@zimmerman.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code Review from the Command Line]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/cli-code-review/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-13T16:14:24-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/cli-code-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I do the bulk of my code reviews from the command line, especially when
reviewing larger changes. I&rsquo;ve built up a number of tools and config
settings that help me dig into the nuances of the code I&rsquo;m reviewing, so
that I can understand it better than if I were just browsing online.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In particular, I&rsquo;ll walk through how I&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li>check out the code in the first place,</li>
<li>get a feel for what changed,</li>
<li>visualize the relationships between the files that changed,</li>
<li>bring up the code diffs in Vim,</li>
<li>leverage the unique power of the editor and the terminal.</li>
</ul>


<p>But first, let&rsquo;s talk briefly about the point of code review in the
first place.</p>

<h2>Code review philosophy</h2>

<p>When I ask that other people review my code, it&rsquo;s an opportunity for me
to teach them about the change I&rsquo;ve just made. When I review someone
else&rsquo;s code, it&rsquo;s to learn something from them. Some other benefits of
code review include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Team awareness (to keep a pulse on what else is going on within your
team).</li>
<li>Finding alternative solutions (maybe there&rsquo;s a small change that lets
us kill two birds with one stone).</li>
</ul>


<p>If this is different from how you think about code review, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PJjmw9TRB7s">check out
this talk</a>. Code review is a powerful tool for
learning and growing a team.</p>

<p>With that out of the way, let&rsquo;s dive into the tools I use to maximize
benefit I get from code review.</p>

<h2>Checking out the code</h2>

<p>The first step to reviewing code in the terminal is to check out the
code in the first place. One option is to simply to <code>git pull</code> and then
<code>git checkout &lt;branch&gt;</code>. But if you happen to be using GitHub, we can
get this down to just one command:</p>

<pre><code>hub pr checkout &lt;pr-number&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>It works using <a href="https://github.com/github/hub">hub</a>, which is a tool that exposes various features of
GitHub from the command line. If the pull request is from someone else&rsquo;s
fork, <code>hub</code> is even smart enough to add their fork as a remote and fetch
it.</p>

<h2>At first glance</h2>

<p>With the branch checked out locally, usually my next step is to get a
feel for what changed. For this, I&rsquo;ve written a git alias that shows:</p>

<ul>
<li>which files changed</li>
<li>how many lines changed in each file (additions and deletions)</li>
<li>how many lines changed overall</li>
</ul>


<p><a class="image-link" href="/images/git-stat.png"><img class="fullwidth" src="/images/git-stat.png" title="git stat" ></a></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the definition of <code>git stat</code> from my <code>~/.gitconfig</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">[alias]
    # list files which have changed since REVIEW_BASE
    # (REVIEW_BASE defaults to 'master' in my zshrc)
    files = !git diff --name-only $(git merge-base HEAD \"$REVIEW_BASE\")

    # Same as above, but with a diff stat instead of just names
    # (better for interactive use)
    stat = !git diff --stat $(git merge-base HEAD \"$REVIEW_BASE\")
</code></pre>

<p>Under the hood, it just works using <code>git diff</code>, <code>git merge-base</code>, and a
personal environment variable <code>REVIEW_BASE</code>.</p>

<p><code>REVIEW_BASE</code> lets us choose which branch to review relative to. Most of
the time, <code>REVIEW_BASE</code> is <code>master</code>, but this isn&rsquo;t always the case! Some
repos branch off of <code>gh-pages</code>. Sometimes I like to review the most
recent commit as if it were its own branch.</p>

<p>To review the code relative so some other base, set <code>REVIEW_BASE</code> before
running <code>git stat</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="bash"># Review between 'gh-pages' and the current branch
REVIEW_BASE=gh-pages git stat

# Review changes made by the last commit of this branch:
REVIEW_BASE=HEAD^ git stat
</code></pre>

<p>I have <code>export REVIEW_BASE=master</code> in my <code>~/.bashrc</code>, because most
projects branch off of <code>master</code>.</p>

<p>Nothing too crazy yet&mdash;GitHub can already do everything we&rsquo;ve seen so
far. Let&rsquo;s start to up the ante.</p>

<h2>Visualizing file change frequency</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve written a short script that shows me a visualization of how
frequently the files involved in this branch change over time:</p>

<p><a class="image-link" href="/images/git-heatmap.png"><img class="fullwidth" src="/images/git-heatmap.png" title="git heatmap" ></a></p>

<p>This command identifies two main things:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Files with lots of changes</strong>.</p>

<p>Files that have changed a lot in the past are likely to change in the
future. I review these files with an eye towards what the <em>next</em>
change will bring.</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Is this change robust enough to still be useful in the future?
Will we throw this out soon after merging it?&rdquo;</em></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Files with few changes</strong>.</p>

<p>Files that aren&rsquo;t changed frequently are more likely to be brittle.
Alternatively, it&rsquo;s often the case that infrequently changed files
stay unchanged because the change is better made elsewhere.</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Does this change challenge an implicit assumption so that some other
part of the code was relying on? Is there a better place for this
change?&rdquo;</em></p></li>
</ul>


<p>Those two commands (<code>git stat</code> and <code>git heatmap</code>) are how I kick off my
code review: getting a birds-eye view of the change and some historical
context for what I&rsquo;m dealing with. Next, I drill down into the
relationships between the files that changed.</p>

<h2>Visualizing relationships between files</h2>

<p>At work I review JavaScript files, so I&rsquo;ve built out this next bit of
tooling specifically for JavaScript.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> It helps to understand
which files import others, so I have a command that computes the
dependency graph of the files changed on this branch:</p>

<p><a class="image-link" href="/images/git-depgraph.png"><img class="fullwidth" src="/images/git-depgraph.png" title="git depgraph" ></a></p>

<p>This is where we start to see some distinct advantages over what GitHub
provides. As you see above, the <code>git depgraph</code> alias calculates the
dependency graph for files changed by this branch. Why is this useful?</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Maybe we want to start reviewing from <code>Provider.js</code>, since it doesn&rsquo;t
depend on any other files that have changed.</p></li>
<li><p>Maybe we want to work the other way: start with <code>Elements.js</code> so we
know the motivation for why <code>Provider.js</code> had to changed in the first
place.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>In either case, we can see the structure of the change. Three files
depend on <code>Elements.js</code>, so it&rsquo;s serving the needs of many modules.
<code>Element.js</code> only has one dependency, etc. Each branch&rsquo;s dependency
graph shows different information; it can be surprising what turns up.</p>

<p>I have the <code>git depgraph</code> alias defined like this:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">[alias]
    depgraph = !git madge image --webpack-config webpack.config.js --basedir . --style solarized-dark src
</code></pre>

<p>Some notes about this definition:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>It depends on the <code>git-madge</code> command, which you can <a href="https://github.com/jez/git-madge">download
and install here</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>It&rsquo;s using <em>this project&rsquo;s</em> <code>webpack.config.js</code> file, so I&rsquo;ve made
this alias local to the repo, rather than available globally.</p></li>
<li><p>It dumps the image to stdout. Above, we used iTerm2&rsquo;s <a href="https://iterm2.com/documentation-images.html">imgcat</a>
program to pipe stdin and dump a raster image to the terminal.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t use iTerm2 or don&rsquo;t want to install <code>imgcat</code>, you can
pipe it to Preview using open<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> (<code>open -f -a Preview</code>) or just
redirect the PNG to a file.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The <code>git depgraph</code> alias is a game changer. It makes it easier to get spun
up in new code bases, helps make sense of large changes, and just looks
plain cool. But at the end of the day, we came here to review some code,
so let&rsquo;s take a look at how we can actually view the diffs of the files
that changed.</p>

<h2>Reviewing the diffs</h2>

<p>To review the diffs, the simplest option is to just run <code>git diff
master..HEAD</code>. This has a bunch of downsides:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>No syntax highlighting (everything is either green or red).</p></li>
<li><p>No surrounding context (for example, GitHub lets you click to expand
lines above or below a diff hunk).</p></li>
<li><p>The diff is &ldquo;unified,&rdquo; instead of split into two columns.</p></li>
<li><p>No way to exclude a specific file (the 300 line diff to your
<code>yarn.lock</code> file is sometimes nice to hide).</p></li>
</ul>


<p>My solution to all of these problems is to view the diffs in Vim, with
the help of two Vim plugins and two git aliases. Before we get to
that, here&rsquo;s a screenshot:</p>

<p><a class="image-link" href="/images/git-review.png"><img class="fullwidth" src="/images/git-review.png" title="git review" ></a></p>

<p>Looks pretty similar to GitHub&rsquo;s interface, with the added bonus that
it&rsquo;s using my favorite colorscheme! The Vim plugins featured are:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-fugitive">tpope/vim-fugitive</a> for showing the side-by-side diff (<code>:Gdiff</code>).</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/airblade/vim-gitgutter">airblade/vim-gitgutter</a> for showing the <code>+/-</code> signs.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jez/vim-colors-solarized">jez/vim-colors-solarized</a> for tweaking the diff highlight
colors.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></li>
</ul>


<p>And to orchestrate the whole thing, I&rsquo;ve set up these two aliases:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">[alias]
  # NOTE: These aliases depend on the `git files` alias from
  # a few sections ago!

    # Open all files changed since REVIEW_BASE in Vim tabs
    # Then, run fugitive's :Gdiff in each tab, and finally
    # tell vim-gitgutter to show +/- for changes since REVIEW_BASE
    review = !vim -p $(git files) +\"tabdo Gdiff $REVIEW_BASE\" +\"let g:gitgutter_diff_base = '$REVIEW_BASE'\"

    # Same as the above, except specify names of files as arguments,
    # instead of opening all files:
    # git reviewone foo.js bar.js
    reviewone = !vim -p +\"tabdo Gdiff $REVIEW_BASE\" +\"let g:gitgutter_diff_base = '$REVIEW_BASE'\"
</code></pre>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how they work:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><code>git review</code> opens each file changed by this branch as a tab in Vim.
Then <code>:Gdiff</code> from vim-fugitive shows the diff in each tab.</p></li>
<li><p><code>git reviewone</code> is like <code>git review</code>, but you specify which
files to open (in case you only want to diff a few).</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Like with the <code>git stat</code> alias, these aliases respect the <code>REVIEW_BASE</code>
environment variable I&rsquo;ve set up in my <code>~/.bashrc</code>. (Scroll back up for
a refresher.) For example, to review all files relative to <code>master</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">REVIEW_BASE=master git review
</code></pre>

<p>At this point, you might think that all we&rsquo;ve done is re-create the
GitHub code review experience in Vim. But actually what we&rsquo;ve done is so
much more powerful.</p>

<h2>Interactive Code Review</h2>

<p>When reviewing on GitHub, the code is completely static&mdash;you can&rsquo;t
change it. Also, because the code is coming from GitHub&rsquo;s servers,
it&rsquo;s laggy when you click around to view related files. By switching our
code review to the terminal, we can now edit files, jump to other files,
and run arbitrary commands at no cost.</p>

<p>It might not be obvious how huge of a win this is, so let&rsquo;s see some
examples. Take this screenshot of the <code>requireElement</code> function. It
moved from <em>above</em> the <code>findElement</code> function to <em>below</em> it (probably
because the former calls the latter):</p>

<p><a class="image-link" href="/images/requireElement01.png"><img class="fullwidth" src="/images/requireElement01.png" title="diff" ></a></p>

<p>But is the location of the <code>requireElement</code> function the only thing
that&rsquo;s changed? By editing the file to move the function back to its
original location, vim-fugitive will automatically recompute the diff.
And in fact, we can see that the <em>type of the argument</em> has changed too,
from <code>string</code> to <code>ElementType</code>:</p>

<p><a class="image-link" href="/images/requireElement02.png"><img class="fullwidth" src="/images/requireElement02.png" title="diff" ></a></p>

<p>If we had been viewing this on GitHub, we might have taken for granted
that the function didn&rsquo;t change. But since we&rsquo;re in our editor, we can
interactively play around with our code and discover things we might
have missed otherwise. The advantages of interactive code review go well
beyond this example:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>In a Flow project, we can ask for the type of a variable.</p></li>
<li><p>In a test file, we can change the test and see if it still passes or
if it now fails.</p></li>
<li><p>We can <code>grep</code> the project for all uses of a function (including files
<em>not</em> changed by this branch).</p></li>
<li><p>We can open up related files for cross-referencing.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>By having the full power of our editor, we can literally retrace the
steps that the author went through to create the pull request. If our
goal is to understand and learn from code review, there&rsquo;s no better way
than walking in the author&rsquo;s shoes.</p>

<h2>Recap</h2>

<p>To recap, here&rsquo;s a list of the tools I use to review code at the command
line:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>hub pr checkout</code></li>
<li><code>git stat</code> to list files that have changed</li>
<li><code>git heatmap</code> to show how frequently these files change</li>
<li><code>git depgraph</code> to show a graph of which files depend on which</li>
<li><code>git review</code> to open diffs of all the files in Vim</li>
<li><code>git reviewone</code> to open diffs for a specific handful of files</li>
</ul>


<p>If you&rsquo;re having trouble incorporating any of these into your workflow,
feel free to reach out and let me know! I&rsquo;m happy to help.</p>

<!-- vim:tw=72
-->

<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>The techniques here apply to any language that you can statically analyze. In particular, I have a rough prototype of everything JavaScript-specific you see here that works with Standard ML instead. If you can find me the dependency information for your favorite language, I&rsquo;d be happy to help you turn it into a visualization.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>The <code>open</code> command is macOS-specific. On Linux, you might want to look at the <code>display</code> command from ImageMagick.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>I&rsquo;ve patched the default Solarized colors for Vim so that lines retain their syntax highlighting in the diff mode, while the backgrounds are highlighted. You can see how this works in this commit: <a href="https://github.com/jez/vim-colors-solarized/commit/bca72cc">https://github.com/jez/vim-colors-solarized/commit/bca72cc</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Show where a Python package is used]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2015/06/12/show-where-a-python-package-is-used/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-12T02:36:05-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2015/06/12/show-where-a-python-package-is-used</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back I was doing some spring cleaning of my Python packages. I noticed
that there were a bunch of packages that I couldn&rsquo;t recall installing. I wanted
to know if I could safely remove them, so I wrote a simple bash script to tell
me called <code>pip-uses</code>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Source</h2>

<p>Rather than post the source here and let it get more out of date every time I
change it, you can find the source <a href="https://github.com/jez/bin/blob/master/pip-uses">on GitHub</a>. It&rsquo;s in my <a href="https://github.com/jez/bin">bin
repository</a>, where I keep my notable helper scripts; feel free to
poke around.</p>

<h2>Motivations</h2>

<p>I was primarily influenced by Homebrew&rsquo;s <code>brew uses</code> command. It does a nice job
of giving you exactly the information you want, and I think the way the command
is named makes sense.</p>

<pre><code class="plain Homebrew: brew uses">$ brew uses --installed pango
imagemagick
</code></pre>

<p><code>pip-uses</code> gives you basically the experience:</p>

<pre><code class="plain Pip: pip-uses">$ pip-uses stevedore
virtualenvwrapper
</code></pre>

<p>In this example, the Python package <code>virtualenvwrapper</code> uses <code>stevedore</code>, just
as <code>imagemagick</code> uses <code>pango</code>. Both commands can save you from accidentally
removing a crucial dependency and answer the burning question, &ldquo;How in the world
did this thing get installed?&rdquo;</p>

<h2>Wish List</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m not doing much Python development these days, but if I had some spare time
I&rsquo;d love for the script to also have these features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Recursive enumeration of dependencies

<ul>
<li>It&rsquo;d be nice if <code>pip-uses</code> kept recursively searching until it found no more
dependencies. This way, it&rsquo;d be easy to see if you could safely uninstall a
whole slew of packages that you&rsquo;re no longer using.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Operate on more than one package

<ul>
<li>I didn&rsquo;t need it at the time, so I didn&rsquo;t implement it, but it&rsquo;d be nice if
the command took a variable amount of arguments and ran the same logic on
all supplied packages.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Integrate with <code>pip</code>

<ul>
<li>Programs like <code>brew</code> and <code>pip</code> allow developers to add &ldquo;external commands&rdquo;
by adding commands to the <code>PATH</code> that look like <code>brew-xyz</code> or <code>git-xyz</code>. I
couldn&rsquo;t find if there was a special way to add external commands to <code>pip</code>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>If you find this script useful and end up implementing one of these feature or
more on top of <code>pip-uses</code>, be sure to send me a Pull Request!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Chrome: A Memory Hog]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2014/12/29/google-chrome-a-memory-hog/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-29T18:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2014/12/29/google-chrome-a-memory-hog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whenever someone complains about a slow computer, the first thing I check is
how many Chrome tabs they have open. Chrome hogs memory like no other. For
users, this means Chrome is snappy and responsive, but oftentimes it comes at
the expense of crowding out other programs. To get an idea of how much memory
Chrome is really using, I wrote a quick bash oneliner.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Why does Chrome Hog Memory?</h2>

<p><a href="http://mobile.extremetech.com/latest/221392-iframe-irony-adblock-plus-is-probably-the-reason-firefox-and-chrome-are-such-memory-hogs">An article posted to Hacker News</a> recently brought some light to
the question of why Chrome and Firefox suck up so much memory: Adblock Plus. The
general idea is that the excessive use of iframes in most websites today ramps
up the amount of processing that Adblock Plus has to do, driving memory usage
through the roof. For more specifics, check out the rest of of the article.</p>

<h2>The Oneliner</h2>

<p>For the impatient, here&rsquo;s the code. It uses standard Unix tools:</p>

<pre><code class="bash Chrome Memory Usage">$ ps -ev | grep -i chrome | awk '{print $12}' | awk '{for(i=1;i&lt;=NF;i++)s+=$i}END{print s}'
</code></pre>

<p>Pretty isn&rsquo;t it? If you want to save this as an alias for handy use, add this
line to your ~/.bashrc (or appropriate configuration file):</p>

<pre><code class="bash Add as an alias">alias chromemem="ps -ev | grep -i chrome | awk '{print \$12}' | awk '{for(i=1;i&lt;=NF;i++)s+=\$i}END{print s}'"
</code></pre>

<p>It outputs a percentage. Here&rsquo;s the alias in action:</p>

<pre><code class="bash Usage">$ chromemem
60
</code></pre>

<h2>Explanation</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s a lot of good stuff going on here, so let&rsquo;s take it step-by-step.</p>

<p>First, we&rsquo;ll need a program that tells us memory usage. I&rsquo;m sure there are many,
but I&rsquo;m familiar with <code>ps</code>. After checking out the man page for a few options, I
came up with <code>ps -ev</code>, to show all information about all processes. Maybe
wasteful, but it works.</p>

<pre><code class="bash ps -ev">$ ps -ev
  PID STAT      TIME  SL  RE PAGEIN      VSZ    RSS   LIM     TSIZ  %CPU %MEM COMMAND
 3473 S      0:54.92   0   0      0  3579092 301244     -        0   6.7  7.2 /Applications/Google C
  365 S      3:03.17   0   0      0  3920732 206808     -        0   0.3  4.9 /Applications/Google C
  983 S      1:29.23   0   0      0  3560272 193860     -        0   0.1  4.6 /Applications/Google C
  395 S      0:13.11   0   0      0  2824936 141644     -        0   0.0  3.4 /Applications/Google C
  422 S      0:27.22   0   0      0  3345796 130796     -        0   0.0  3.1 /Applications/Google C
  ...
</code></pre>

<p>Notice that there&rsquo;s a convenient column describing memory usage as a percentage
of total available memory, as well as what command is being run in that
process. Let&rsquo;s make sure that we&rsquo;re looking at only the processes running
some sort of Chrome service before totaling up the memory. We can find these
lines with <code>ps -ev | grep -i chrome</code> (the -i means case-insensitive). Due to the
way I clipped the previous sample output, nothing changes in the first five
lines, but rest assured: we&rsquo;re only looking at Chrome processes now.</p>

<p>Now it&rsquo;s time to get rid of all the other nonsense that we included with <code>ps
-ev</code>. Luckily, there&rsquo;s a handy tool called <code>awk</code> that makes parsing text by
column easy. If we want to print the 12th column (which just so happens to
contain the memory consumption!) we can do <code>awk '{print $12}'</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="bash ps -ev | grep -i chrome | awk '{print $12}'">$ ps -ev | grep -i chrome | awk '{print $12}'
7.2
5.1
4.6
3.4
3.2
...
</code></pre>

<p>Finally, I found myself needing a way to add up a column of numbers. A quick
Google search led me to <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/2572495/read-from-file-and-add-numbers">this StackOverflow question</a>, and I picked the
<code>awk</code> solution because I knew I could just pipe the input to awk (as opposed to
having to do weird hacks to get it to work with a bash for loop):</p>

<pre><code class="bash Final Solution">$ ps -emv | grep -i chrome | awk '{print $12}' | awk '{for(i=1;i&lt;=NF;i++)s+=$i}END{print s}'
60.4
</code></pre>

<p>Of course, you could change the last <code>awk</code> command to print out something
fancier like</p>

<pre><code class="bash Final Solution">$ ps -emv | grep -i chrome | awk '{print $12}' | awk '{for(i=1;i&lt;=NF;i++)s+=$i}END{print "Chrome is using "s"% of total memory."}'
Chrome is using 60.4% of total memory.
</code></pre>

<p>There you have it! Bash oneliners save the day yet again.</p>

<h2>Update</h2>

<p>After writing this article, I stopped using Ad Block Plus, and I noticed a
significant drop in Chrome&rsquo;s memory usage. Obviously, though, that came at the
cost of not blocking ads! Also, from time to time I would encounter a site that
seemed sluggish, presumably because of all the ads attempting to be loaded. My
simple solution to this was just to disable JavaScript on that page (I use an
extension called Quick JavaScript Switcher), but this wasn&rsquo;t an automated
solution.</p>

<p>Then I discovered <a href="https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock">μBlock</a>, an &ldquo;efficient blocker for Chromium and
Firefox.&rdquo; The fancy graphs on it&rsquo;s homepage convinced me to give it a shot, and
from what I can tell so far it&rsquo;s responsive and effective.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vim as a Man Page Viewer]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2014/12/20/vim-as-a-man-page-viewer/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-20T21:17:46-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2014/12/20/vim-as-a-man-page-viewer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Man pages are an essential part of every developer&rsquo;s workflow. Unfortunately,
the default system pager <code>less</code> isn&rsquo;t the best interface. That&rsquo;s why I wrote a
Vim plugin and a short shell function to take care of opening man pages in Vim.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Plugin</h2>

<p>If you&rsquo;re eager to dive right into the source or to install the plugin, head on
over to the <a href="https://github.com/jez/vim-superman">GitHub repository</a>. It&rsquo;s a whopping 32 SLOC, so feel
free to peek under the hood.</p>

<h2>Why?</h2>

<p>You might be thinking, &ldquo;But Jake, <code>man</code> works just fine for me, why would I
switch?&rdquo; I&rsquo;m glad you asked!</p>

<h3>Mouse Support</h3>

<p>The first reason why I was interested in getting man pages to open in Vim was
because I wanted to be able to scroll with the mouse. When I have to read man
pages for a long time, usually as a part of some more all-encompasing bit of
research, I find scrolling to be a much better interface for quickly perusing
the content of a man page.</p>

<h3>Syntax Highlighting</h3>

<p>As it turns out, man pages have a syntax to them, and Vim does a pretty
excellent job at highlighting them. Rather than talk about it, here are some
screenshots. Note how code samples (C system calls and library functions) are
also syntax highlighted appropriately.</p>

<pre><code class="bash Example 1">vman vim
</code></pre>

<p><a class="image-link" href="/images/vim.1.png"><img src="/images/vim.1.png"></a></p>

<pre><code class="bash Example 2">vman 3 printf
</code></pre>

<p><a class="image-link" href="/images/printf.3.png"><img src="/images/printf.3.png"></a></p>

<h3>All the benefits of Vim</h3>

<p>While <code>less</code> makes a good effort to emulate certain Vim keybindings (or maybe
it&rsquo;s the other way around, I don&rsquo;t know which came first), <code>less</code> certainly
falls short of the full power of Vim.</p>

<p>For example, once you&rsquo;ve opened a man page in Vim, you can open a new tab or
split side-by-side with the man page. Especially if you&rsquo;re switching between Vim
and the man page often, being able to open man pages in tabs or splits is
invaluable.</p>

<h2>Mine doesn&rsquo;t look like yours!</h2>

<p>A couple of my other plugins are showing in the screenshots above. I&rsquo;m using the
<a href="https://github.com/altercation/vim-colors-solarized">Solarized Dark color scheme</a>, the plugin
<a href="https://github.com/bling/vim-airline">vim-airline</a> to take over the statuslines at the very top and
bottom, and iTerm2 on Mac OS X 10.10.</p>

<p>You can see my complete configuration <a href="https://github.com/jez/dotfiles">on GitHub</a>.</p>

<h2>Feedback</h2>

<p>As a matter of fact, this was my first Vim plugin! If you notice anything out of
place, even if it&rsquo;s a small detail, I&rsquo;d love to hear it. Make no assumptions
about the reasoning behind why certain decisions were made, because I have none
XD</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
