<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Bits, Bytes, and Words]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-07-18T19:29:06-04:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.jez.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Zimmerman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jake@zimmerman.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Joys of the Craft]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2014/12/13/the-joys-of-the-craft/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-13T20:52:09-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2014/12/13/the-joys-of-the-craft</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while ago, I was given the book <em>The Mythical Man-Month</em>, by Frederick P. Brooks, Jr. I finally have some time to sit down and read it, and I&rsquo;m loving it. In the first chapter, this quote on &ldquo;the joys of the craft&rdquo; (i.e., programming) struck me as particularly on point:</p>

<!-- more -->


<blockquote><h3>The Joys of the Craft</h3>

<p>Why is programming fun? What delights may its practitioner expect as his reward?</p>

<p>First is the sheer joy of making things. As the child delights in his mud pie, so the adult enjoys building things, especially things of his own design. I think this delight must be an image of God&rsquo;s delight in making things, a delight shown in the distinctness and newness of each leaf and each snowflake.</p>

<p>Second is the pleasure of making things that are useful to other people. Deep within, we want others to use our work and to find it helpful. In this respect the programming system is not essentially different from the child&rsquo;s first clay pencil holder &ldquo;for Daddy&rsquo;s office.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Third is the fascination of fashioning complex puzzle-like objects of interlocking moving parts and watching them work in subtle cycles, playing out the consequences of principles built in from the beginning. The programmed computer has all the fascination of the pinball machine or the jukebox mechanism, carried to the ultimate.</p>

<p>Fourth is the joy of always learning, which springs from the nonrepearing nature of the task. In one way or another the problem is ever new, and its solver learns something: sometimes practical, sometimes theoretical, and sometimes both.</p>

<p>Finally, there is the delight of working in such a tractable medium. The programmer, like the poet, works only slightly removed from pure thought-stuff. He builds his castles in the air, from air, creating by exertion of the imagination. Few media of creation are so flexible, so easy to polish and rework, so readily capable of realizing grand conceptual structures. (As we shall see later, this very tractability has its own problems.)</p>

<p>Yet the program construct, unlike the poet&rsquo;s words, is real in the sense that it moves and works, producing visible outputs separate from the construct itself. It prints results, draws pictures, produces sounds, moves arms. The magic of myth and legend has come true in our time. One types the correct incantation on a keyboard, and a display screen comes to life, showing things that never were nor could be.</p>

<p>Programming then is fun because it gratifies creative longings built deep within us and delights sensibilities we have in common with all men.</p>

<p>&ndash; &ldquo;The Tar Pit&rdquo;, <em>The Mythical Man-Month</em>, Frederick P. Brooks Jr.</p></blockquote>

<p>Brooks of course follows this up with &ldquo;The Woes of the Craft&rdquo;, which is equally on point. I&rsquo;m only a few pages in, but I already feel like, respectfully, I&rsquo;ve learned more than I did in all of Tech Comm (<a href="https://enr-apps.as.cmu.edu/open/SOC/SOCServlet/courseDetails?COURSE=15221&amp;SEMESTER=F14">15-221</a>). I would absolutely recommend it to anyone considering pursing software engineering!</p>

<p>- - -

### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://avatars5.githubusercontent.com/u/5544532?v=4&u=4640ad0fd7da51dc2a84c5ae9d11a96677b4d185&s=400"><img class="left" src="https://avatars5.githubusercontent.com/u/5544532?v=4&u=4640ad0fd7da51dc2a84c5ae9d11a96677b4d185&s=400" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on
[GitHub][g] or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. If this post was about one of
my open source projects, make sure to star it on GitHub! I love hearing what
people think, so feel free to open an issue or send me an email.
 [g]: https://www.github.com/jez/
 [h]: https://jez.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
