<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: recitation | Bits, Bytes, and Words]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/categories/recitation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-06-13T12:21:12-04:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.jez.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Zimmerman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jake@zimmerman.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[System Fω and Parameterization]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/system-f-param/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-27T22:14:45-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/system-f-param</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I first learned about System F<sub>ω</sub>, I was confused about
the difference between <code>∀(t.τ)</code> (forall types) and <code>λ(u.c)</code> (type
abstractions) for a long time, but recently I finally grasped the
difference! Both of these constructs have to do with parameterization
(factoring out a variable so that it&rsquo;s bound), but the two types have
drastically different meanings.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Questions</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;ll start off with some questions to keep in mind throughout these
notes. Our goals by the end are to understand what the questions are
asking, and have at least a partial&mdash;if not complete&mdash;answer to each.</p>

<p>First, consider this code.</p>

<pre><code class="sml">datatype 'a list = Nil | Cons of 'a * 'a list
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>What really is &ldquo;<code>list</code>&rdquo; in this code?</li>
<li>Or put another way, how would we define <code>list</code> in System
F<sub>ω</sub>?</li>
</ul>


<p>Thinking more broadly,</p>

<ul>
<li>What separates <code>∀(t.τ)</code> and <code>λ(u.c)</code>?</li>
<li>What is parameterization, and how does it relate to these things?</li>
</ul>


<h2>System F<sub>ω</sub></h2>

<p>The answers to most of these questions rely on a solid definition of
System F<sub>ω</sub>. We&rsquo;ll be using this setup.</p>

<pre><code>Kind κ ::= * | κ → κ | ···

           abstract       concrete      arity/valence
Con c  ::= ···
         | arr(c₁; c₂)    c₁ → c₂       (Con, Con)Con
         | all{κ}(u.c)    ∀(u ∷ κ). c   (Kind, Con.Con)Con
         | lam{κ}(u.c)    λ(u ∷ κ). c   (Kind, Con.Con)Con
         | app(c₁; c₂)    c₁(c₂)        (Con, Con)Con
</code></pre>

<p>Some points to note:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>∀(u ∷ κ). c</code> and <code>λ(u ∷ κ). c</code> have the same arity.</li>
<li><code>∀(u ∷ κ). c</code> and <code>λ(u ∷ κ). c</code> both <em>bind</em> a constructor variable.
This makes these two operators <em>parametric</em>.</li>
<li>Only <code>λ(u ∷ κ). c</code> has a matching elim form: <code>c₁(c₂)</code>.
(There are no elim forms for <code>c₁ → c₂</code> and <code>∀(u ∷ κ). c</code>, because they
construct types of kind <code>*</code>. This will be important later.)</li>
</ul>


<p>It&rsquo;ll also be important to have these two inference rules for kinding:</p>

<p>$$
\frac{
  \Delta, u :: \kappa \vdash c :: *
}{
  \Delta \vdash \forall(u :: \kappa). \, c :: *
}\;(\texttt{forall-kind})
$$
$$
\frac{
  \Delta, u :: \kappa \vdash c :: \kappa&#8217;
}{
  \Delta \vdash \lambda(u :: \kappa). \, c :: \kappa \to \kappa&#8217;
}\;(\texttt{lambda-kind})
$$</p>

<h2>Defining the <code>list</code> Constructor</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take another look at this datatype definition from above:</p>

<pre><code class="sml">datatype 'a list = Nil | Cons of 'a * 'a list
</code></pre>

<p>We&rsquo;ve <a href="/variables-in-types/">already seen</a> how to encode the type of lists
of integers using inductive types:</p>

<pre><code>intlist = μ(t. 1 + (int × t))
</code></pre>

<p>Knowing what we know about System F (the &ldquo;<strong>polymorphic</strong> lambda
calculus&rdquo;), our next question should be &ldquo;how do we encode
<strong>polymorphic</strong> lists?&rdquo; Or more specifically, which of these two
operators (<code>λ</code> or <code>∀</code>) should we pick, and why?</p>

<p>First, we should be more specific, because there&rsquo;s a difference between
<code>list</code> and <code>'a list</code>. Let&rsquo;s start off with defining <code>list</code> in
particular. From what we know of programming in Standard ML, we can do
things like:</p>

<pre><code class="sml">(* Apply 'int' to 'list' function! *)
type grades = int list

type key = string
type val = real

(* Apply '(key, val)' to 'list' function! *)
type updates = (key, val) list
</code></pre>

<p>If we look really closely, what&rsquo;s actually happening here is that <code>list</code>
is a type-level <em>function</em> that returns a type (and we use the <code>type foo
= ...</code> syntax to store that returned type in a variable).<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Since <code>list</code> is actually a function from types to types, it must have
an arrow kind: <code>* → *</code>. Looking back at our two inference rules for
kinding, we see only one rule that lets us introduce an arrow kind: <code>λ(u
∷ κ). c</code>. On the other hand, <code>∀(u ∷ κ). c</code> must have kind <code>*</code>; it
<em>can&rsquo;t</em> be used to define type constructors.</p>

<p>Step 1: define list constructor? Check:</p>

<pre><code>list = λ(α ∷ *). μ(t. 1 + (α × t)))
</code></pre>

<h2>Defining Polymorphic Lists</h2>

<p>It doesn&rsquo;t stop with the above definition, because it&rsquo;s still not
<em>polymorphic</em>. In particular, we can&rsquo;t just go write functions on
polymorphic lists with code like this:</p>

<pre><code class="sml">fun foo (x : list) = (* ··· *)
</code></pre>

<p>We can&rsquo;t say <code>x : list</code> because all intermediate terms in a given
program have to type check as a type of kind <code>*</code>, whereas <code>list ∷ * →
*</code>. Another way of saying this: there isn&rsquo;t any way to introduce a value
of type <code>list</code> because there&rsquo;s no way to introduce values with arrow
kinds.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, we <em>can</em> write this:</p>

<pre><code class="sml">fun foo (x : 'a list) = (* ··· *)
</code></pre>

<p>When you get down to it, this is actually kind of weird. Why is it okay
to use <code>'a list</code>? I never defined <code>'a</code> anywhere, so wouldn&rsquo;t that make
it an unbound variable?</p>

<p>It turns out that when we use type variables like this, SML
automatically binds them for us by inserting <code>∀</code>s into our code. In
particular, it implicitly infers a type like this:</p>

<pre><code class="sml">val foo : forall 'a. 'a list -&gt; ()
</code></pre>

<p>SML inserts this <code>forall</code> automatically because its type system is a bit
less polymorphic than System F<sub>ω</sub>&rsquo;s. Some might call this a
drawback, though it does save us from typing <code>forall</code> annotations
ourselves. And really, for most anything else we&rsquo;d call a &ldquo;drawback&rdquo; of
this design, SML makes up the difference with modules.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>Step 2: make polymorphic list for use in annotation? Check:</p>

<pre><code>α list = ∀(α ∷ *). list(α)
</code></pre>

<h2>Variables &amp; Parameterization</h2>

<p>Tada! We&rsquo;ve figured out how to take a list datatype from SML and encode
it in System F<sub>ω</sub>, using these two definitions:</p>

<pre><code>  list = λ(α ∷ *). μ(t. 1 + (α × t)))
α list = ∀(α ∷ *). list(α)
</code></pre>

<p>We could end here, but there&rsquo;s one more interesting point. If we look
back, we started out with the <code>∀</code> and <code>λ</code> operators having the same
arity, but somewhere along the way their behaviors differed. <code>λ</code> was
used to create type constructors, while <code>∀</code> was used to introduce
polymorphism.</p>

<p>Where did this split come from? What distinguishes <code>∀</code> as being the
go-to type for polymorphism, while <code>λ</code> makes type constructors
(type-to-type functions)? Recall one of the earliest ideas we teach in
<a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~rwh/courses/ppl/">15-312</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip; the core idea carries over from school mathematics, namely
that <strong>a variable is an unknown, or a place-holder, whose meaning is
given by substitution.</strong></p>

<p>&ndash; Harper, <em>Practical Foundations for Programming Languages</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Variables are given meaning by substitution, so we can look to the
appropriate substitutions to uncover the meaning and the differences
between <code>λ</code> and <code>∀</code>. Let&rsquo;s first look at the substitution for <code>λ</code>:</p>

<p>$$
\frac{
  \Delta, u :: \kappa_1 \vdash c_2 :: \kappa_2 \qquad \Delta \vdash c_1
  :: \kappa_1
}{
  \Delta \vdash (\lambda(u :: \kappa_1). \, c_2)(c_1) \equiv  [c_1/u]c_2 :: \kappa_2
}
$$</p>

<p>We can think of this as saying &ldquo;when you apply one type to another, the
second type gets full access to the first type to construct a new type.&rdquo;
We notice that the substitution here is completely <strong>internal to the
type system</strong>.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p>On the other hand, the substitution for <code>∀</code> <strong>bridges the gap</strong> from
types to terms:</p>

<p>$$
\frac{
  \Delta \, \Gamma, e : \forall (u :: \kappa). \tau \qquad \Delta \vdash c :: \kappa
}{
  \Delta \, \Gamma \vdash e[c] : [c/u]\tau
}
$$
$$
\frac{
  \mbox{}
}{
  (\Lambda u. \, e)[\tau] \mapsto [\tau / u]e
}
$$</p>

<p>When we&rsquo;re type checking a polymorphic type application, we don&rsquo;t get to
know anything about the type parameter <code>u</code> other than its kind. But when
we&rsquo;re running a program and get to the evaluation of a polymorphic type
application, we substitute the concrete <code>τ</code> directly in for <code>u</code> in <code>e</code>,
which bridges the gap from the type-level to the term-level.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, all the interesting stuff came from using
functions (aka, something parameterized by a value) in cool ways. Isn&rsquo;t
that baffling? Functions are so powerful that they seem to always pop up
at the heart of the most interesting constructs. I think it&rsquo;s
straight-up amazing that something so simple can at the same time be
that powerful. Functions!</p>

<!-- vim:tw=72
-->

<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>It&rsquo;s easy to not notice at first that type definitions are really function calls because in Standard ML, the type function applications are backwards. Instead of <code>f(x)</code>, it&rsquo;s <code>x f</code>. This is more similar to how we actually think when we see a function. Consider <code>h(g(f(x)))</code> (or another way: <code>h . g . f $ x</code>). We read this as &ldquo;take x, do f, pass that to g, and pass that to h&rdquo;. Why not write <code>x f g h</code> in the first place?<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Other languages (like Haskell or PureScript) have a language feature called &ldquo;Rank-N Types&rdquo; which is really just a fancy way of saying &ldquo;you can put the <code>forall a.</code> anywhere you want.&rdquo; Oftentimes, this makes it harder for the compiler to infer where the variable bindings are, so you sometimes have to use more annotations than you might if you weren&rsquo;t using Rank-N types.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>It&rsquo;s not super relevant to this discussion, but this inference rule is for the judgement defining equality of type constructors. This comes up all over the place when you&rsquo;re writing a compiler for SML. If this sounds interesting, definitely take 15-417 HOT Compilation!<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Variables in Types]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/variables-in-types/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-25T05:17:31-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/variables-in-types</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>These are some recitation notes for an ad-hoc recitation I gave for the
class <a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~rwh/courses/ppl/">15-312 Principles of Programming Languages</a>. It was probably
my favorite 312 recitation content-wise, because it&rsquo;s the first
recitation where we&rsquo;ve covered enough stuff to where we can really start
connecting the dots.</p>

<p><strong>Abstract</strong>:</p>

<blockquote><p>We&rsquo;ve seen a number of examples in class of types which use variables.
Having variables in our type systems lends a great deal of power to
languages using these type systems. We&rsquo;re going to look at how
variables are used in generic programming, inductive &amp; coinductive
types, and polymorphic types.</p></blockquote>

<h3>→ <a href="/notes/variables-in-types.pdf">Variables in Types</a></h3>

<!-- vim:tw=72
-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Recitation Notes]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/recitation-notes-tag/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-24T17:40:10-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/recitation-notes-tag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!-- Empty header to prevent first paragraph from being big -->


<p></p>


<p>One thing I miss from being a teaching assistant is getting to write up
recitation and lecture notes for technical topics. Like with teaching
any other subject, writing up explanations for interesting things I&rsquo;ve
found helps me round out what concepts are still confusing. I also miss
getting to make nice LaTeX-typeset PDFs.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Recitation notes are distinguished from normal blog posts in that
they&rsquo;ll cover more CS theory-oriented topics and will be more
<em>instructive</em> than <em>experience-based</em>. All recitation notes are tagged
with the tag <code>recitation</code>.</p>

<h3>→ <a href="/categories/#recitation">All posts tagged with <code>recitation</code></a></h3>

<p>I might &ldquo;cross post&rdquo; a few of the more interesting existing recitation
handouts I&rsquo;ve made over the years (though some of them make a
heavy-handed assumption that you&rsquo;re in the class currently).</p>

<!-- vim:tw=72
-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
