<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Github | Jake Zimmerman]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/categories/github/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-20T01:03:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.zimmerman.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Zimmerman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jake@zimmerman.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running a VPS: Log 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/19/running-a-vps-log-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-19T23:10:51-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/19/running-a-vps-log-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Managing Dotfiles Across Machines</h1>

<p>You could say I&rsquo;m a bit of a geek when it comes to configuring my terminal environment; this obsession has led me to concoct ever-elaborate setup scripts and configuration files. On top of this, between my laptop&rsquo;s multiple boot environments, the servers I use for school, work, and ScottyLabs, and now <a href="/2014/06/19/running-a-vps-log-0">metagross</a>, keeping my configuration files in sync is a must. I handle it swiftly using a combination of git and rcm.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>My Scripts</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve put a decent amount of time into my dotfiles. I like to think they&rsquo;re pretty good. That being said, I&rsquo;m not about to go over every piece of them, because that would bore even me. I might come back to these pieces in a series on getting started with the terminal (aimed at incoming CS freshmen and other up-and-coming hackers), but for now, a link will suffice.</p>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles/">Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles</a></h4>

<h2>rcm + git</h2>

<p>rcm, short for rc file (as in .bash<b>rc</b>, .vim<b>rc</b>) management, is a tool that manages symlinks between dotfiles in one directory and your home directory. This is cool because, once all your config files contained in one folder, they can be tracked with git for version control without having to put your entire <code>$HOME</code> directory inside a git repo.</p>

<p>On a single machine, rcm works like this. You have one directory (usually <code>~/.dotfiles</code>, but configurable to any directory) which stores all the config files. In here, all files which are meant to be tracked and symlinked do <em>not</em> include the prefixed &lsquo;<code>.</code>&rsquo;; instead, it is added as part of the linking process. After installation, which is easily handled through the brew formula, the .deb, or the Makefile, there are a couple of new tools available.</p>

<p>The first worth mentioning is <code>man 7 rcm</code>, which documents what was just installed. Taking a glance at this page, we see that rcm is actually a suite of tools: <code>lsrc</code>, <code>mkrc</code>, <code>rcdn</code>, and <code>rcup</code>. While all these tools are useful, the most important is <code>rcup</code>. After collecting all your dotfiles into <code>~/.dotfiles</code>, simply executing <code>rcup</code> symlinks all the necessary files to their appropriate locations.</p>

<p>From here, you get all the benefits of git, like pushing to GitHub, collaborating with others, lightweight branching, and syncing files easily even when your workflow is distributed across many servers.</p>

<h2>Caveats</h2>

<p>To be fair, I don&rsquo;t use <code>rcm</code> in the way I think it&rsquo;s creators imagined it would be used. Specifically, the software includes certain provisions to designate which files should affect various machines using a tag system. While it could possibly work, in my mind it&rsquo;s much more tedious than what I&rsquo;ve come up with.</p>

<p>Succinctly, the issue is this: when cloning a repo and running <code>rcup</code> for the first time, you can&rsquo;t easily say &ldquo;this is my VPS, it&rsquo;s running Debian GNU/Linux, has these system binaries installed, and therefore should start up using these methods and scripts&rdquo;. For this, we&rsquo;re on our own.</p>

<h2>Installation</h2>

<p>The solution I came up with regarding a multiple-environment workflow deals with handling all the necessary machine-dependent configuration within my dotfiles <em>themselves</em>. That way I can minimize code reuse and have everything in one convenient file. As a result, <a href="https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles/tree/master/bash_profile">my bash_profile</a> is a bit lengthy at about 300 lines, and it has three large case statements, but I make all this up through deployment. Deployment is <strong>incredibly</strong> swift. Again, You can take a look at the file to see how it works, but when I had finished <a href="/2014/06/19/running-a-vps-log-1">locking down my server</a>, these are the only configuration commands I had to run:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Installing rcm and dotfiles </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;install rcm using deb and dpkg&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;<span class="nv">$ </span>wget &lt;a <span class="nv">href</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;https://thoughtbot.github.io/rcm/debs/rcm_1.2.3-1_all.deb&quot;</span>&gt;https://thoughtbot.github.io/rcm/debs/rcm_1.2.3-1_all.deb&lt;/a&gt;
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>sudo dpkg -i rcm_1.2.3-1_all.deb&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;clone dotfiles down, into the ~/.dotfiles directory&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;<span class="nv">$ </span>git clone &lt;a <span class="nv">href</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles&quot;</span>&gt;https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles&lt;/a&gt; ~/.dotfiles&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;make the symlinks&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;<span class="nv">$ </span>rcup
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>Voilà! After that, I had my sick bash prompt, my <a href="/2014/06/11/update-your-software-its-the-law/">snazzy update function</a>, my delightful vim colorscheme, solarized dir colors&mdash;the list goes on and on.</p>

<p>Sure, it&rsquo;s taken a bit of effort to get the point where I can run these commands and have it Just Work, but doing that work once means that from now on, whenever I sit down at a new work computer, a new VPS, a new laptop, or some other workstation, I&rsquo;m only a few commands away from my favorite settings.</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on [Twitter][t], checking out my tinkerings on [GitHub][g], or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. I'd love to hear what you think about what I've managed to put together, so feel free to comment, tweet at me, or send me an email.
 [t]: http://www.twitter.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [g]: http://www.github.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [h]: http://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GitHub Pages Custom Domains]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/05/06/github-pages-custom-domains/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T03:15:35-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/05/06/github-pages-custom-domains</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I stumbled at first getting the DNS configured for my blog, because I&rsquo;ve got a slighty more complicated setup than normal. I decided to supplement the documentation <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> gives by recounting my personal example and the setup that worked.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>If you&rsquo;ve never heard of <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> for web hosting, you should definitely check it out. You basically get free hosting for any static (i.e. plain HTML or <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a>-served) website with git-push-to-deploy. You can even configure your site to be listed at a custom domain according to <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/setting-up-a-custom-domain-with-github-pages">these</a> instructions, which are pretty thorough. I feel like it&rsquo;d help, though, to supplement this documentation with a fairly common example setup.</p>

<h2>My setup</h2>

<p>I have two sites which I want to host using the <code>zimmerman.io</code> domain name: my <a href="//blog.zimmerman.io">blog</a> and my <a href="//www.zimmerman.io">personal site</a>. I host my personal site at <a href="//www.zimmerman.io">www.zimmerman.io</a>, but you can also navigate to <a href="//zimmerman.io">zimmerman.io</a> and end up in the same places as before. It&rsquo;s served as a User Page from <a href="https://www.github.com/Z1MM32M4N/z1mm32m4n.github.io">this repo</a>.</p>

<p>I host my blog at <a href="//blog.zimmerman.io">blog.zimmerman.io</a>, and it&rsquo;s served as a Project Page in <a href="https://www.github.com/Z1MM32M4N/blog/">this repo</a>.</p>

<h2>What the instructions say</h2>

<p>The instructions say a few things very clearly (yay, documentation!).</p>

<p>First, if I want to use a custom subdomain (like what I&rsquo;m doing for my blog) to host a repo, I can add a <code>CNAME</code> record with my DNS provider that points to what is in my case <code>z1mm32m4n.github.io</code>. This was counterintuitive to me, because I thought at first that this would make my blog.zimmerman.io domain redirect to my personal site, but that&rsquo;s not how GitHub handles it. (They&rsquo;re smarter than that.)</p>

<p>At the same time, I need to put a file in the root of the blog&rsquo;s repo (in the <code>gh-pages</code> branch because it&rsquo;s a Project Page), called <code>CNAME</code> (<a href="https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/blog/blob/gh-pages/CNAME">view source</a>) with the contents &lsquo;blog.zimmerman.io&rsquo;. After a little while, the DNS tables will update and everything here should work: I can now view my <em>blog</em> where I want it.</p>

<h2>What the instructions say, but not so clearly</h2>

<p>The next bit gave me some trouble at first (probably just because I was being impatient while the DNS tables were updating). The end goal was to have the <code>www</code> subdomain host my site and have the <code>@</code> (top-level or apex) domain redirect there. If you read carefully, the instructions say to do three things:</p>

<ol>
<li> Make the <code>CNAME</code> file (<a href="https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/z1mm32m4n.github.io/blob/master/CNAME">view source</a>) in my (User) Pages repository contain <code>www.zimmerman.io</code>. <strong>This</strong> is the domain at which I do want my site to be visible.</li>
<li> Create a <code>CNAME</code> record with my DNS provider pointing to <code>z1mm32m4n.github.io</code> for the <code>www</code> subdomain. From a technical standpoint on the DNS provider&rsquo;s side of things, this is the same thing we did before with the <code>blog</code> subdomain.</li>
<li> Create an <code>A</code> record pointing the <code>@</code> domain towards GitHub using the IP address they specify.</li>
</ol>


<p>This last step is where you have to have a little faith: nowhere is there an explicit file telling GitHub, &ldquo;If you get a request from zimmerman.io, send it to me!&rdquo; GitHub merely notices that there <strong>is</strong> a repo with a CNAME containing &lsquo;<strong>www</strong>.zimmerman.io&rsquo;, and so they say, &ldquo;Well, we may as well send this <strong>top level</strong> domain to the <strong>www</strong> domain referenced over here&hellip; I&rsquo;ve got nothing better to do.&rdquo;</p>

<p>This was a little confusing at first, because if I wanted the opposite direction (www.zimmerman.io to redirect to zimmerman.io), I would have still created a CNAME file, but it would have contained <code>zimmerman.io</code> and I would have created an <code>A</code> record with my DNS provider, not an actual CNAME. (I still did have to create both the <code>A</code> and <code>CNAME</code> in the end, but in this setup, the <code>A</code> record is referenced in the <code>CNAME</code> file, if that makes any sense.)</p>

<h2>Recap</h2>

<h3>My CNAME Files</h3>

<ul>
<li> For www.zimmerman.io:

<ul>
<li> CNAME file contains <code>www.zimmerman.io</code></li>
<li> CNAME file resides in <code>master</code> branch of User Pages repo for Z1MM32M4N</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> For blog.zimmerman.io

<ul>
<li> CNAME file contains <code>blog.zimmerman.io</code></li>
<li> CNAME file resides in <code>gh-pages</code> branch of Project Pages repo for Z1MM32M4N/blog</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h3>My DNS Config</h3>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a screenshot of what my records look like with my DNS provider, in case this was still unclear.</p>

<p><a href="/images/DNS-config.jpg"><img src="/images/DNS-config.jpg"></a></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m personally using <a href="https://www.gandi.net/">Gandi</a> for domain registration because they had the cheapest <code>.io</code> TLD registration, but their interface takes some getting used to. (It was certainly still worth the deal I got.)</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on [Twitter][t], checking out my tinkerings on [GitHub][g], or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. I'd love to hear what you think about what I've managed to put together, so feel free to comment, tweet at me, or send me an email.
 [t]: http://www.twitter.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [g]: http://www.github.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [h]: http://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
