<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Meta | Bits, Bytes, and Words]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/categories/meta/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-14T18:21:24-04:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.jez.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Zimmerman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jake@zimmerman.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New GitHub Username]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2015/02/03/new-github-username/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-03T04:01:04-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2015/02/03/new-github-username</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve changed my GitHub username from Z1MM32M4N to jez (hopefully it&rsquo;ll be a
little easier to type now!). Make sure you update any remote URLs for repos of
mine that you&rsquo;ve cloned.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Updating your Git remotes</h2>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve cloned one of my repositories, you can update it&rsquo;s URL by running</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ git remote -v
</code></pre>

<p>to check the current remote URL, which should look something like
<code>https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/&lt;repo name&gt;</code>. Then, you can run</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ git remote set-url origin https://github.com/jez/&lt;repo name&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>to actually change the URL.</p>

<p>Because of the way that GitHub handles username changes, you should be able to
continue using the current URLs at least for the time being, but any time you
pull you&rsquo;ll get a message from GitHub asking to update the remote URLs.</p>

<p>I tried to update all links referencing Z1MM32M4N to use the new username, but
I&rsquo;m sure I&rsquo;ve missed a few. If you find a &ldquo;broken&rdquo; link, shoot me a message
letting me know!</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on
[GitHub][g] or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. If this post was about one of
my open source projects, make sure to star it on GitHub! I love hearing what
people think, so feel free to comment, open an issue, or send me an email.
 [g]: https://www.github.com/jez/
 [h]: https://jez.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HPSTR: An Octopress Theme]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2014/06/04/hpstr-an-octopress-theme/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-04T21:51:41-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2014/06/04/hpstr-an-octopress-theme</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In case you didn&rsquo;t notice, we&rsquo;re rocking a new theme: <a href="https://github.com/jez/hpstr-theme">HPSTR for Octopress</a>! Ported from the <a href="https://github.com/mmistakes/hpstr-jekyll-theme">theme of the same name</a> for Jekyll, this theme has a bunch of cool new features that make the theme easier to use and more customizable.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Before I begin, I have to give a huge shout out to <a href="https://github.com/mmistakes/">mmistakes</a> for crafting such an impeccable set of stylesheets and Jekyll templates. I could talk this theme up all day, but I think that the results speak for themselves. Even more praiseworthy is that the entire source code is licensed under the GPL, enabling anyone to take the source and build upon it. And on that note, I&rsquo;d like to unveil what <em>I&rsquo;ve</em> built.</p>

<h1>Ported to Octopress</h1>

<p>The theme was originally implemented for a vanilla Jekyll blog. Personally, I find the automation tools provided by Octopress to be incredibly helpful, and I didn&rsquo;t want to give these up to be able to deploy this theme. As a result, I had to tweak a few things in order to get it to work with a standard Octopress installation.</p>

<h2>Less to Sass</h2>

<p>The HPSTR theme was originally built using Less to compile its stylesheets. Octopress uses Sass under Compass instead&ndash;a decision which I love: the rich library of plugins that Compass provides is ridiculous. Thus, this was the first step of the port.</p>

<p>After a quick Google search I stumbled upon <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/14970224/anyone-know-of-a-good-way-to-convert-from-less-to-sass">this question</a> on Stack Overflow, which surprisingly took care of the vast majority of the conversion, leveraging mere text replacement. From there, it was mostly a matter of slugging through the Less docs to find out what a particular function did, jumping over to the Compass/Sass docs to find a corresponding mixin, and repeating.</p>

<h2>Sass to Compass</h2>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t stop after I had the vanilla Sass working. One of Compass&rsquo;s coolest features is that you don&rsquo;t have to repeat yourself: there are mixins for seemingly everything, and when there aren&rsquo;t, there are 3<sup>rd</sup> party plugins. Thus, the next phase of the port was to see how much of the code I could reduce to compass mixins.</p>

<p>For the most part, this stage affected CSS3 properties which need vendor prefixes, to include keyframe animations. The keyframe animations are particularly worthy of a mention because I found a handy plugin called <a href="https://github.com/ericam/compass-animation">compass-animation</a> to take care of them. It works as easily as any other Compass mixin, from installation to use.</p>

<h2>Octopress Mannerisms</h2>

<p>There are a few things that Octopress users can expect to be reasonably similar from one deployment to the next, and I wanted to ensure that as many of the features dually implemented by mmistakes and Octopress used the syntax or conformed to the style set forth by Octopress. A small example of this: the <code>page.link</code> and <code>page.external_url</code> properties. Defined by the old and new themes respectively, both accomplish a similar purpose. Each specifies that the main purpose of the post is to link to a different page. Not wanting to break the service for current Octopress users, I tried to convert as many of these subtleties.</p>

<p>On top of this, I restructured a lot of the original code so that someone used to customizing an Octopress theme would feel more at home when checking out the source for this theme, even if some of the particulars were different. This applied mostly to the Sass directory structure, but also to the templates.</p>

<h1>More Powerful Customization</h1>

<p>One of the many ways Octopress adds value on top of Jekyll is the ease with which you can get a Jekyll blog up and running, and subsequently customize and tweak that theme. This was one area where I felt that the original Jekyll theme fell short. The original stylesheets had a somewhat decent set of variables (in <code>less/variables.less</code>) that would allow you to customize the colors and font faces, but the method for customizing the size of the font was wonky (larger values produced smaller fonts), and the various mixins employed to handle setting the sizes were confusing.</p>

<p>To solve this, I added <em>loads</em> of new variables handling the font sizes and line heights on a per-component basis, while also providing a master switch to easily resize everything. My theme also differs here from the original in that it&rsquo;s default font size is slightly larger for normal paragraph text (the whole reason why I cared about customizing the font size in the first place!).</p>

<h1>Like what you see?</h1>

<p>This theme is in no way perfect, from the styles to the compatibility with the vast array of Octopress options. If my support for your favorite feature is lacking or absent altogether, patch it up and submit a pull request on <a href="https://github.com/jez/hpstr-theme">GitHub</a>!</p>

<p><strong>I&rsquo;d also love to hear about your installation process.</strong> If something didn&rsquo;t quite work out right when installing the theme from GitHub or everything went super smoothly, tell me on GitHub in an issue, on <a href="https://www.twitter.com/Z1MM32M4N">Twitter</a>, in the comments below, or in an <a href="mailto:jake@zimmerman.io">email</a>. Seriously!</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on
[GitHub][g] or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. If this post was about one of
my open source projects, make sure to star it on GitHub! I love hearing what
people think, so feel free to comment, open an issue, or send me an email.
 [g]: https://www.github.com/jez/
 [h]: https://jez.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shiny New Octopress Blog]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2014/05/06/shiny-new-octopress-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T01:41:14-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2014/05/06/shiny-new-octopress-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The below is a post I originally posted on my first (failed) blog. While that blog didn&rsquo;t work out quite right, I hope to keep many of the same ideals at heart when continuing (and hopefully maintaining) this blog, so I decided I may as well repost it here.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>README</h2>

<p>It is currently 2:14am on Wednesday, October 16, 2013. “Today,” (well really yesterday) at a <a href="//scottylabs.org">ScottyLabs</a> meeting (a student organization at Carnegie Mellon (CMU) that lies at the nexus of design and technology), my interest in the group showed through enough to the point where they entrusted a few low-level permissions to help out developing the various projects they’ve been working on right now, namely <a href="//print.scottylabs.org">Print@ScottyLabs</a>. As happens all too often, I am realizing just how much I have to learn: about technology, about college, about people, about everything.</p>

<p>But looking around (maybe I haven’t looked very far), I don’t see one central place where I can go to get help with all of this stuff, or at least the tech stuff. Obviously I can ask people if I really need it. The support structures are supposedly in place. In my experience, though, when you approach people for help on general topics, you get tossed back to the Internet as they say, “Google it.”  While things certainly can be found on the Internet, for someone who just wants to be able to read about the answer without being overwhelmed by the details, it seems like there’s <strong>no good place to start</strong>.</p>

<h2>What I Want</h2>

<p>In this spirit of aggregating pieces of knowledge on the interwebs, I’d like to document my process of learning and researching. Here are a few of my goals:</p>

<h3>Personal Reference</h3>

<p>I want something to look back on if I can’t remember something. Say I’m wondering why in the world I even started this thing: I could look back at this post. It&rsquo;s one thing to be able to find a site you had visited in your history, but it&rsquo;s another to be able to read about exactly what you were using that site to do. Documentation is <em>vastly</em> underappreciated.</p>

<h3>Metacognition</h3>

<p>Everyone says it’s good to think about the way you think. I spent a lot of time in high school contemplating the effects of information overload due to the Internet, and I’m sure that as I start down this process, it’s only going to get deeper. In writing down my thoughts like this, I’d like to get some sort of structure to my learning so that I can keep the floodgates at bay.</p>

<h3>Public Roadmap</h3>

<p>If there are 300+ million people in America and 7+ billion people around the world, then <em>statistically</em>, there <em>has</em> to be someone just like me who’d like to have such a road map. If this is you, it’s my hope that these ramblings are useful.</p>

<h2>Where to Next</h2>

<p>So it’s getting pretty late and I’d like to get back to what I was learning about: MVC. (EDIT: It&rsquo;s still late, and it&rsquo;s even worse this time because I have exams this week&hellip; A+ Jake&hellip;) So hopefully, I’ll have time to keep developing this, whatever “this” is. I’ve been told that “There are only two hard things in Computer Science: cache invalidation, naming things, and off-by-one errors.” I have no idea what cache invalidation is (yet!), but the “naming things” bit is spot on.</p>

<p>So here goes nothing&hellip; I’m sure that in the very least it’ll be fun to look over these entries 5, 10, 20 years from now and think about how quickly things changed.</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on
[GitHub][g] or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. If this post was about one of
my open source projects, make sure to star it on GitHub! I love hearing what
people think, so feel free to comment, open an issue, or send me an email.
 [g]: https://www.github.com/jez/
 [h]: https://jez.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
