<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: unix | Bits, Bytes, and Words]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/categories/unix/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.jez.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-26T17:48:52-04:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.jez.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Zimmerman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jake@zimmerman.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Chrome: A Memory Hog]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2014/12/29/google-chrome-a-memory-hog/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-29T18:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2014/12/29/google-chrome-a-memory-hog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whenever someone complains about a slow computer, the first thing I check is
how many Chrome tabs they have open. Chrome hogs memory like no other. For
users, this means Chrome is snappy and responsive, but oftentimes it comes at
the expense of crowding out other programs. To get an idea of how much memory
Chrome is really using, I wrote a quick bash oneliner.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Why does Chrome Hog Memory?</h2>

<p><a href="http://mobile.extremetech.com/latest/221392-iframe-irony-adblock-plus-is-probably-the-reason-firefox-and-chrome-are-such-memory-hogs">An article posted to Hacker News</a> recently brought some light to
the question of why Chrome and Firefox suck up so much memory: Adblock Plus. The
general idea is that the excessive use of iframes in most websites today ramps
up the amount of processing that Adblock Plus has to do, driving memory usage
through the roof. For more specifics, check out the rest of of the article.</p>

<h2>The Oneliner</h2>

<p>For the impatient, here&rsquo;s the code. It uses standard Unix tools:</p>

<pre><code class="bash Chrome Memory Usage">$ ps -ev | grep -i chrome | awk '{print $12}' | awk '{for(i=1;i&lt;=NF;i++)s+=$i}END{print s}'
</code></pre>

<p>Pretty isn&rsquo;t it? If you want to save this as an alias for handy use, add this
line to your ~/.bashrc (or appropriate configuration file):</p>

<pre><code class="bash Add as an alias">alias chromemem="ps -ev | grep -i chrome | awk '{print \$12}' | awk '{for(i=1;i&lt;=NF;i++)s+=\$i}END{print s}'"
</code></pre>

<p>It outputs a percentage. Here&rsquo;s the alias in action:</p>

<pre><code class="bash Usage">$ chromemem
60
</code></pre>

<h2>Explanation</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s a lot of good stuff going on here, so let&rsquo;s take it step-by-step.</p>

<p>First, we&rsquo;ll need a program that tells us memory usage. I&rsquo;m sure there are many,
but I&rsquo;m familiar with <code>ps</code>. After checking out the man page for a few options, I
came up with <code>ps -ev</code>, to show all information about all processes. Maybe
wasteful, but it works.</p>

<pre><code class="bash ps -ev">$ ps -ev
  PID STAT      TIME  SL  RE PAGEIN      VSZ    RSS   LIM     TSIZ  %CPU %MEM COMMAND
 3473 S      0:54.92   0   0      0  3579092 301244     -        0   6.7  7.2 /Applications/Google C
  365 S      3:03.17   0   0      0  3920732 206808     -        0   0.3  4.9 /Applications/Google C
  983 S      1:29.23   0   0      0  3560272 193860     -        0   0.1  4.6 /Applications/Google C
  395 S      0:13.11   0   0      0  2824936 141644     -        0   0.0  3.4 /Applications/Google C
  422 S      0:27.22   0   0      0  3345796 130796     -        0   0.0  3.1 /Applications/Google C
  ...
</code></pre>

<p>Notice that there&rsquo;s a convenient column describing memory usage as a percentage
of total available memory, as well as what command is being run in that
process. Let&rsquo;s make sure that we&rsquo;re looking at only the processes running
some sort of Chrome service before totaling up the memory. We can find these
lines with <code>ps -ev | grep -i chrome</code> (the -i means case-insensitive). Due to the
way I clipped the previous sample output, nothing changes in the first five
lines, but rest assured: we&rsquo;re only looking at Chrome processes now.</p>

<p>Now it&rsquo;s time to get rid of all the other nonsense that we included with <code>ps
-ev</code>. Luckily, there&rsquo;s a handy tool called <code>awk</code> that makes parsing text by
column easy. If we want to print the 12th column (which just so happens to
contain the memory consumption!) we can do <code>awk '{print $12}'</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="bash ps -ev | grep -i chrome | awk '{print $12}'">$ ps -ev | grep -i chrome | awk '{print $12}'
7.2
5.1
4.6
3.4
3.2
...
</code></pre>

<p>Finally, I found myself needing a way to add up a column of numbers. A quick
Google search led me to <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/2572495/read-from-file-and-add-numbers">this StackOverflow question</a>, and I picked the
<code>awk</code> solution because I knew I could just pipe the input to awk (as opposed to
having to do weird hacks to get it to work with a bash for loop):</p>

<pre><code class="bash Final Solution">$ ps -emv | grep -i chrome | awk '{print $12}' | awk '{for(i=1;i&lt;=NF;i++)s+=$i}END{print s}'
60.4
</code></pre>

<p>Of course, you could change the last <code>awk</code> command to print out something
fancier like</p>

<pre><code class="bash Final Solution">$ ps -emv | grep -i chrome | awk '{print $12}' | awk '{for(i=1;i&lt;=NF;i++)s+=$i}END{print "Chrome is using "s"% of total memory."}'
Chrome is using 60.4% of total memory.
</code></pre>

<p>There you have it! Bash oneliners save the day yet again.</p>

<h2>Update</h2>

<p>After writing this article, I stopped using Ad Block Plus, and I noticed a
significant drop in Chrome&rsquo;s memory usage. Obviously, though, that came at the
cost of not blocking ads! Also, from time to time I would encounter a site that
seemed sluggish, presumably because of all the ads attempting to be loaded. My
simple solution to this was just to disable JavaScript on that page (I use an
extension called Quick JavaScript Switcher), but this wasn&rsquo;t an automated
solution.</p>

<p>Then I discovered <a href="https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock">μBlock</a>, an &ldquo;efficient blocker for Chromium and
Firefox.&rdquo; The fancy graphs on it&rsquo;s homepage convinced me to give it a shot, and
from what I can tell so far it&rsquo;s responsive and effective.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Offline LaTeX Development]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.jez.io/2014/10/06/offline-latex-development/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-06T18:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.jez.io/2014/10/06/offline-latex-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While online clients like ShareLaTeX or writeLaTeX are popular for getting started with LaTeX quickly, developing LaTeX locally with Vim and the command line is my preferred LaTeX workflow. In this post, I&rsquo;ll describe the changes I&rsquo;ve made that make working with LaTeX on the command line a seamless experience.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Install LaTeX</h2>

<p>Obviously, to work with LaTeX locally, you&rsquo;ll need LaTeX installed. To check if you already have it installed, you can run <code>which pdflatex</code>. If it&rsquo;s installed, this command will tell you the path to program. Otherwise, it won&rsquo;t print anything.</p>

<h3>On Linux</h3>

<p>Installing LaTeX on Linux isn&rsquo;t too bad. Usually it&rsquo;s included in your distribution&rsquo;s package manager. I&rsquo;ll be focusing on OS X for the majority of this post though, so Google around if you end up having trouble.</p>

<h3>On OS X</h3>

<p>To install LaTeX on a Mac, we&rsquo;ll be installing MacTeX, which includes the command line LaTeX utilities as well as a couple graphical clients for LaTeX development. You can try compiling from source, but as Homebrew points out when you try to <code>brew install linux</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="plain brew install latex">$ brew install latex
Error: No available formula for latex
Installing TeX from source is weird and gross, requires a lot of patches,
and only builds 32-bit (and thus can't use Homebrew deps on Snow Leopard.)

We recommend using a MacTeX distribution: http://www.tug.org/mactex/
</code></pre>

<p>With that in mind, head on over to <a href="http://www.tug.org/mactex/">http://www.tug.org/mactex/</a> and download the file <code>MacTeX.pkg</code>. Once this has downloaded and you&rsquo;ve clicked through the installer, you should be ready to go with LaTeX. Verify this by running <code>which pdflatex</code> again.</p>

<h2>Use Vim</h2>

<p>The biggest productivity improvement you gain from developing LaTeX locally is that you get to use Vim. Make sure you have a nice colorscheme for both your terminal and for Vim. <strong>I can&rsquo;t stress enough how important it is to make your terminal look nice</strong>: you want to enjoy your terminal experience, and this is one of the easiest ways to do so.</p>

<h2>Use Make</h2>

<p>Compiling LaTeX is pretty straightforward. To generate a PDF, all you have to do is run the command</p>

<pre><code class="bash pdflatex">$ pdflatex &lt;myfile&gt;.tex
</code></pre>

<p>And you&rsquo;ll get a file called <code>&lt;myfile&gt;.pdf</code> in the current directory, plus some intermediate files. We can go one step further and put a bunch of useful build targets into a Makefile and use it to build our PDF:</p>

<pre><code class="make LaTeX Makefile https://gist.github.com/jez/b248a409d19c9f1c94cd"># NOTE: Change "written" to the name of your TeX file with no extension
TARGET=written

all: $(TARGET).pdf

## Generalized rule: how to build a .pdf from each .tex
LATEXPDFS=$(patsubst %.tex,%.pdf,$(wildcard *.tex))
$(LATEXPDFS): %.pdf: %.tex
  pdflatex -interaction nonstopmode $(patsubst %.pdf,%.tex,$@)

clean:
  rm *.aux *.log || true

veryclean: clean
  rm $(TARGET).pdf

view: $(TARGET).pdf
  if [ "Darwin" = "$(shell uname)" ]; then open $(TARGET).pdf ; else evince $(TARGET).pdf ; fi

submit: $(TARGET).pdf
  cp $(TARGET).pdf ../

print: $(TARGET).pdf
  lpr $(TARGET).pdf

.PHONY: all clean veryclean view print
</code></pre>

<p>If you save this to a file called <code>Makefile</code> in the same directory as your LaTeX file, we can just run <code>make</code> instead of running <code>pdflatex &lt;myfile&gt;.tex</code>!</p>

<p>As you can see, there are a bunch of other handy targets here:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>make clean</code> will remove all intermediate files that are created.</li>
<li><code>make veryclean</code> will remove all intermediate files and the compiled PDF file.</li>
<li><code>make view</code> will compile the file and then open it up in a PDF viewer (if you&rsquo;re on OS X, or on Linux and have <code>evince</code> installed).</li>
<li><code>make print</code> will send your document to the default printer with the default options for that printer.</li>
<li><code>make submit</code> will copy your file into the parent directory. This is handy when you&rsquo;re working in a subfolder on an assignment to isolate the intermediate files, but your class has provided a handin script that needs the PDF file to be in the parent directory.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Workflow Tips</h2>

<p>Right now, our workflow looks like this:</p>

<ul>
<li>Create TeX file</li>
<li>Edit in Vim</li>
<li>Switch to terminal</li>
<li>Run make view to compile and view</li>
</ul>


<p>We can actually optimize this workflow to one less step: we don&rsquo;t have to get out of Vim to run make!</p>

<p>Vim has a command <code>:make</code> that will look for a Makefile in the current directory and run it&rsquo;s <code>all</code> target. It also takes a target as an optional argument, so we can do <code>:make view</code> to compile and view the document from within Vim!</p>

<p>Taking this one step further, we can add a command to shorten this. If we add</p>

<pre><code class="vim Save, Compile and View in Vim">command WV w | make view
</code></pre>

<p>to our <code>.vimrc</code>, we&rsquo;ll only have to type <code>:WV</code> to save, compile, and view our PDF output.</p>

<h2>Wrap Up</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s it! I like this experience for a bunch of reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>It&rsquo;s faster</strong>. Compiling LaTeX without having to wait for a web client to load is really nice.</li>
<li><strong>It&rsquo;s more stable</strong>. You can still edit, compile, and view your work if you don&rsquo;t have access to the Internet.</li>
<li><strong>It&rsquo;s faster</strong>. Using Vim to edit text is much more convenient than a standard text editor.</li>
</ul>


<p>Do you have a LaTeX tip, a fancier Makefile, or a favorite vim plugin for LaTeX? Share it in the comments!</p>

<h2><a href="/2015/01/10/offline-latex-development-part-2/">Part 2</a>!</h2>

<p>Actually that&rsquo;s not it, there&rsquo;s more! I wrote a <a href="/2015/01/10/offline-latex-development-part-2/">Part 2</a> to this post, which you
should definitely check out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
