<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Intro | Bits, Bytes, and Words]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/categories/intro/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-15T17:36:30-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.zimmerman.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Zimmerman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jake@zimmerman.io]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running a VPS: Log 0]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/19/running-a-vps-log-0/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-19T20:45:29-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/06/19/running-a-vps-log-0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since last Christmas, I&rsquo;ve had a raspberry pi running as a server at my home back in Wisconsin. I had tons of plans for this little guy, but I quickly discovered that he was going to be a bit <em>too</em> little for most of them. Thus, I am now the proud sysadmin of my own virtual private server.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Hosting</h2>

<p>Because at this point in my life I&rsquo;m moving around too much to host my own server somewhere, I decided to contract this part out. I didn&rsquo;t look around too much at VPS providers, but I eventually settled in on DigitalOcean, because it was both recommended at the CClub talk and the most cost-effective of the all the providers I checked. For $10 per month I get a 1-core processor, 1GB of RAM, 30GB of SSD storage, and 2TB of network data transfer. More than enough for a casual VPS.</p>

<h2><a href="http://plusbryan.com/my-first-5-minutes-on-a-server-or-essential-security-for-linux-servers">Safety First</a></h2>

<p>Especially in light of recent security and privacy breeches, the first thing to do on any server is to lock it down. For that, I followed <a href="http://plusbryan.com/my-first-5-minutes-on-a-server-or-essential-security-for-linux-servers">these instructions</a>, with a few modifications.</p>

<p>The post goes over setting up a few simple daemons and setup commands that can be completed in 5 minutes if you&rsquo;ve done this before or half an hour if you want to stop and read up on all the protocols as you go. While I won&rsquo;t reiterate the steps, the list includes setting up the root and an additional sudo user, installing <a href="http://www.fail2ban.org/wiki/index.php/Main_Page">fail2ban</a> for combating brute-force login attempts, setting up ssh logins, setting up a firewall with <a href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UncomplicatedFirewall">Uncomplicated Firewall</a>, and a few other sanity checks.</p>

<h2>Personalization</h2>

<p>At this point, the server was safe, but I still couldn&rsquo;t call it &ldquo;mine.&rdquo; My .bash_profile, .vimrc, and all my other configuration scripts were missing. Fortunately, I had prepared for this moment, and getting everything in working order was incredibly easy. Because there&rsquo;s so much to talk about, I&rsquo;ll be [writing about it] in another post, but in the meantime, I&rsquo;m using a program called <a href="https://github.com/thoughtbot/rcm">rcm</a> that turns <a href="https://github.com/Z1MM32M4N/dotfiles">GitHub</a> into the perfect place to store configuration scripts.</p>

<p>I also spent a long time pondering the consequences of <a href="http://xkcd.com/910/">this comic</a>. Eventually I settled on the name of my favorite Pokemon: Metagross. So without further ado, I&rsquo;d like to introduce my shiny new login message:</p>

<center>
<a class="image-link" href="/images/metagross-motd.png"><img src="/images/metagross-motd.png"></a>
</center>


<h2>Onwards</h2>

<p>So there we are! I&rsquo;ve got a bunch of things in the works and even more things planned, so it should be a nice, long-running summer project.</p>

<hr />

<h3>For the Curious</h3>

<p>While I didn&rsquo;t end up using my raspberry pi very extensively, I did manage to get a few things out of it. For one, it gave me my first experiences using Arch Linux. Admittedly, I didn&rsquo;t get the full experience as it came essentially pre-loaded with it, but it was an experience nonetheless. At some point, once I&rsquo;ve settled into living in one place for more than a few months, I plan on building a desktop and running Arch for the lulz.</p>

<p>Also, and this part is still the biggest reason why I keep it up, is that I can run the No-IP Dynamic Update Client as a daemon to keep tabs on the public IP address for my house back in Wisconsin. This lets me do cool things, like ssh into my raspi from anywhere, administer my family&rsquo;s wireless router when it breaks, and potentially log into one of their computers if I needed to (although whenever I do remote into their computer&rsquo;s, I almost always use the Chrome Remote Desktop Client because it&rsquo;s incredibly easy to use but still entirely full-featured).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shiny New Octopress Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/05/06/shiny-new-octopress-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T00:41:14-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zimmerman.io/2014/05/06/shiny-new-octopress-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The below is a post I originally posted on my first (failed) blog. While that blog didn&rsquo;t work out quite right, I hope to keep many of the same ideals at heart when continuing (and hopefully maintaining) this blog, so I decided I may as well repost it here.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>README</h2>

<p>It is currently 2:14am on Wednesday, October 16, 2013. “Today,” (well really yesterday) at a <a href="//scottylabs.org">ScottyLabs</a> meeting (a student organization at Carnegie Mellon (CMU) that lies at the nexus of design and technology), my interest in the group showed through enough to the point where they entrusted a few low-level permissions to help out developing the various projects they’ve been working on right now, namely <a href="//print.scottylabs.org">Print@ScottyLabs</a>. As happens all too often, I am realizing just how much I have to learn: about technology, about college, about people, about everything.</p>

<p>But looking around (maybe I haven’t looked very far), I don’t see one central place where I can go to get help with all of this stuff, or at least the tech stuff. Obviously I can ask people if I really need it. The support structures are supposedly in place. In my experience, though, when you approach people for help on general topics, you get tossed back to the Internet as they say, “Google it.”  While things certainly can be found on the Internet, for someone who just wants to be able to read about the answer without being overwhelmed by the details, it seems like there’s <strong>no good place to start</strong>.</p>

<h2>What I Want</h2>

<p>In this spirit of aggregating pieces of knowledge on the interwebs, I’d like to document my process of learning and researching. Here are a few of my goals:</p>

<h3>Personal Reference</h3>

<p>I want something to look back on if I can’t remember something. Say I’m wondering why in the world I even started this thing: I could look back at this post. It&rsquo;s one thing to be able to find a site you had visited in your history, but it&rsquo;s another to be able to read about exactly what you were using that site to do. Documentation is <em>vastly</em> underappreciated.</p>

<h3>Metacognition</h3>

<p>Everyone says it’s good to think about the way you think. I spent a lot of time in high school contemplating the effects of information overload due to the Internet, and I’m sure that as I start down this process, it’s only going to get deeper. In writing down my thoughts like this, I’d like to get some sort of structure to my learning so that I can keep the floodgates at bay.</p>

<h3>Public Roadmap</h3>

<p>If there are 300+ million people in America and 7+ billion people around the world, then <em>statistically</em>, there <em>has</em> to be someone just like me who’d like to have such a road map. If this is you, it’s my hope that these ramblings are useful.</p>

<h2>Where to Next</h2>

<p>So it’s getting pretty late and I’d like to get back to what I was learning about: MVC. (EDIT: It&rsquo;s still late, and it&rsquo;s even worse this time because I have exams this week&hellip; A+ Jake&hellip;) So hopefully, I’ll have time to keep developing this, whatever “this” is. I’ve been told that “There are only two hard things in Computer Science: cache invalidation, naming things, and off-by-one errors.” I have no idea what cache invalidation is (yet!), but the “naming things” bit is spot on.</p>

<p>So here goes nothing&hellip; I’m sure that in the very least it’ll be fun to look over these entries 5, 10, 20 years from now and think about how quickly things changed.</p>

<p>- - - - -
<br>
### Jake on the Web
<a class="image-link" href="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/463467877593407488/hfwJj20L.jpeg" width="135" height="135"></a>
If you cared enough to read that far, you should consider following me on [Twitter][t], checking out my tinkerings on [GitHub][g], or paying a visit to [my homepage][h]. I&#8217;d love to hear what you think about what I&#8217;ve managed to put together, so feel free to comment, tweet at me, or send me an email.
 [t]: http://www.twitter.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [g]: http://www.github.com/Z1MM32M4N/
 [h]: http://www.zimmerman.io/
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
